<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Vindiciae vindiciarum, or, A further manifestation of M.J.C., his contradictions instanced in Vindiciae clavium being a rejoinder to his reply (to some few of those many contradictions) in his last book called, The way of Congregationall churches cleared, part 2 / by D.C.</title>
            <author>Cawdrey, Daniel, 1588-1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 120 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31449</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1641</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23919</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07922528</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07922528</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40476</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31449)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40476)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1201:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Vindiciae vindiciarum, or, A further manifestation of M.J.C., his contradictions instanced in Vindiciae clavium being a rejoinder to his reply (to some few of those many contradictions) in his last book called, The way of Congregationall churches cleared, part 2 / by D.C.</title>
                  <author>Cawdrey, Daniel, 1588-1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.M. for Christopher Meredith,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cotton, John, 1584-1652. --  Way of Congregational churches cleared.</term>
               <term>Congregational churches --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40476:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40476:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>VINDICIAE VINDICIAR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M,</hi> OR A further manifeſtation of M. <hi>J. C.</hi> his contradictions, inſtanced in <hi>Vindiciae Clavium,</hi> BEING A Rejoinder to his Reply (to ſome few of thoſe many Contradictions) in his laſt Book, called, <hi>The Way of Congregationall Churches Cleared,</hi> Part. 2.</p>
            <p>By <hi>D. C.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JAMES 1.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>A double minded man is unſtable in all his waies.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Veritas ſimplex, error multiplex.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>Chriſtopher Meredith</hi> at the Sign of the Crane in <hi>Pauls</hi>-Church-yard, 1651.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:40476:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40476:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>VINDICIAE VINDICIAR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M.</hi> CHAPTER I.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTION I.</hi> Of the Church to which Chriſt committed the power of the Keys.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Queſtion between us in this firſt <hi>Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> was concerning the meaning of thoſe words, <hi>The Kingdom of heaven,</hi> in Mat. 16.19. and conſequently, <hi>What Church</hi> it was to which the <hi>Keys</hi> were by Chriſt committed. For the finding out where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I proceeded by a diſtinction, It the <hi>Kingdom of heaven</hi> did there ſignifie the <hi>Church;</hi> it muſt either be taken 1. Of the <hi>Inviſible</hi> Church of true believers, oppoſed to Reprobates. 2. The <hi>Catholike vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible</hi> Church oppoſed to Heathens; or (as you in anſwering the firſt queſtion <hi>pag.</hi> 2. of Keys) to the World. 3. Or a <hi>particular Congregation.</hi> Give me leave I pray to be now little more exact in ſtating the queſtion, by enquiring what is the ſenſe of thoſe words, and the <hi>terms</hi> of the queſtion.<note place="margin">1. What is meant by the Kingdom of Heaven.
<list>
                        <item>1. Of glory.</item>
                        <item>2. Of grace.</item>
                        <item>3. Of both.</item>
                     </list>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. What is meant by the <hi>Kingdom of heaven,</hi> whereof the <hi>Keys</hi> are here given to <hi>Peter.</hi> The <hi>Kingdom of heaven</hi> in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture uſage, ſignifies, either 1. The Kingdom of glory (as fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently) or 2. The Kingdom of <hi>grace,</hi> as in ſome places, grace being
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40476:3"/> the beginning of or firſt ſtep into that Kingdom of glory, Or 3. It ſignifies both the Kingdom of grace and glory. And we are both agreed, that in this text it ſignifies both: My firſt words in <hi>Vind. Clav.</hi> grant it, and you affirm it; <q>[By the Kingdom of heaven here, is meant, both the Kingdom of grace, which is the Church, and the Kingdom of glory which is in the higheſt heavens.]</q> And you give a very good reaſon for it; <q>[For (ſay you) Chriſt giving to <hi>Peter</hi> the Keys of the Kingdom of heaven, conveyeth therewith not only this pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to binde on earth (that is, in the Church on earth, for he gave him no power at all to binde in the world; <hi>the Kingdom of Chriſt is not of this world</hi>) but he gives him alſo this privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, That what he bound on earth ſhould be bound in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: And heaven being diſtinguiſhed from the Church on earth, muſt needs be meant of the kingdom of glory.]</q> Let this be remembred againſt anon.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">2. What that Church is to whom the Keys are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</note>2. The <hi>Kingdom of heaven,</hi> ſignifying the <hi>Church</hi> (and that both in heaven and earth (both triumphant and militant) for what he cals in the 19. verſe The <hi>Kingdom of heaven,</hi> he cals in the 18, verſe, <hi>his Church.</hi>) We muſt enquire what <hi>Church,</hi> or what part of his <hi>Church</hi> it is to which the Keys are given: This Queſtion (I confeſſe) is needleſſe, in reſpect to the Text it ſelf; For it ſayes nothing at all of giving the Keys to the Church, but of giving to <hi>Peter</hi> the Keys of the Church, called by the name of the <hi>Kingdom of heaven,</hi> which is worth your ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation. For it is your <hi>importunity</hi> rather that hath cauſed this queſtion, who have <hi>arrogated</hi> the <hi>Keys</hi> out of the hands of <hi>Peter,</hi> to whom Chriſt in this text gave them, and given them to the <hi>Church,</hi> that is (incongruouſly) to the <hi>Kingdom of heaven:</hi> but of his more anon: We ſhall therefore follow you (rather then the Text) and conſider, what is meant here by the <hi>Church:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Church is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtically for, 1. The whole Church, either 1. The inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Catholike Church.</note> It is taken in the Eccleſiaſticall uſe (for I paſſe by the civill) in many ſenſes: briefly thus.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For the <hi>whole Church,</hi> called commonly by the name of the <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> and that in a double notion:</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Inviſible Catholike Church,</hi> the whole number of the Elect, in heaven and earth, in all places and times: ſo it is commonly underſtood, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.23, 25, 26, 27, 32. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.18. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:40476:3"/>2.<note place="margin">2. The viſible Catholike Church.</note> The <hi>Catholike viſible Church</hi> containing the whole multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of <hi>profeſſors</hi> of Religion, elect or hypocrites, in this world, as oppoſed to the Church of the Jews, or to the men of the world: So it is taken <hi>Act.</hi> 5.11. and 8.3. at leaſt as <hi>contra-diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed</hi> to a particular Congregation.</p>
               <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. For ſome parts of the Church in combination, 1. A particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that a Church 1. Politicall.</note> For ſome <hi>parts</hi> of the Church, to whom is attributed the name of the whole, from their <hi>Aſſembling</hi> together in different combinations: And then it is taken,</p>
               <p n="1">1. For a <hi>particular Congregation,</hi> or particular Saints, aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled together; and this again is by ſome diſtinguiſhed into</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Politicall</hi> or <hi>Organicall,</hi> conſiſting of <hi>Officers</hi> and <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> as the <hi>Integrall</hi> parts thereof; and thoſe Congregations being members of the <hi>Catholike viſible</hi> Church, as <hi>Integrall</hi> parts thereof. The texts are obvious where it is ſo taken.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Entitive</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Entitive.</note> (as they call it) or <hi>Eſſentiall,</hi> conſiſting only of a company of Saints combined by conſent, without any <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers:</hi> So the Reverend M. <hi>Hooker</hi> and others uſe to ſpeak. But (that I may note it by the way) to me, This <hi>Entitive Church</hi> (ſo called) ſeems rather to be a notion, never exiſting, but in mens fancy, in the Reſolution or Analyſis of a Church into its materials, or elſe it is very <hi>improperly</hi> called a Church: To my obſervation and underſtanding hitherto, there is not in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſuch an <hi>Entitive Church</hi> to be found, gathered, and exiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without any Officers. That place <hi>Act.</hi> 15.4.22. produced by the learned and judicious M. <hi>Hudſon,</hi> in his <hi>vind. pag.</hi> 3. where he ſaies <q>[Church is taken for the members as diſtinct from Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, ]</q> doth not hold out a <hi>Church Entitive,</hi> without any Officers (for that had Officers) but only diſtinguiſheth the <hi>Integrall</hi> parts of that Church, into Officers and members: The ſenſe is no more but this, either it means, The Apoſtles and Elders, with the reſt of the <hi>Church members;</hi> or (if the Church was then diſtinguiſhed into divers Congregations) it takes in all the Congregations as the whole Church: for ſo the words are expreſſed <hi>verſ.</hi> 22. the <hi>whole Church:</hi> And your ſelf call that which we call the <hi>Catholike viſible Church,</hi> by the name of the <hi>whole Church;</hi> when you ſay here <hi>pag.</hi> 5. <q>[The whole Church (or which is all one, the Catholike Church) may be viſible in her ſingular members]</q> However it appears not, that then
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40476:4"/> there was any <hi>Entitive</hi> Church, exiſting without Officers. That other Text, <hi>Act.</hi> 14.23. ſeems rather to imply it <q>[And when they had ordained them Elders in every Church ]</q> as if there had been Churches gathered and exiſting without any Officers. But the ſenſe of the place may be this, when they had gathered and ſetled <hi>Churches,</hi> of Elders and members, both at once; So ſoon as there were <hi>members</hi> enough to make a <hi>Church,</hi> they or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained them <hi>Elders,</hi> and made them a <hi>politicall</hi> Church: If not ſo, yet the Apoſtles <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> were <hi>Officers</hi> to them, before; <hi>Catholick</hi> Officers to them as yet members only of the <hi>Catholick Church;</hi> and now they being to depart ordained them <hi>Elders</hi> in their ſtead, and made them particular <hi>politicall</hi> Churches. If thoſe members were not confederate by conſent (whereof the Scripture ſaies nothing) they themſelves ſay, they were not a <hi>Church,</hi> but only Materials of a Church, and ſo mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the <hi>Catholike Church</hi> only, or of none. I ſhall ſay ſomething more to this in another place; I preſcribe not to any mans judgement, but ſubmit it to conſideration, and proceed.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">2. The Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Church.</note>2. As a <hi>Congregation</hi> is called a Church, as afore; ſo ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the <hi>Officers</hi> not only diſtinguiſhed, but as ſeparated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a <hi>Court,</hi> are called the <hi>Church:</hi> Our Saviour alluding to that cuſtome amongſt the Jews; and not relating to a <hi>Congregatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall</hi> Church not yet known, nor yet in being: And now the queſtion returns upon us, To <hi>what Church</hi> of all theſe, the keys were committed. Some ſay one thing, ſome another: you ſay, to the <hi>particular Congregation,</hi> which we ſhall conſider, when we have added that,</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">3. How the Keys are given to the Church, whether</note>3. It is to be conſidered in this queſtion, when the <hi>Keys</hi> are ſaid to be given to the <hi>Church</hi> (which is never ſaid expreſly in Scripture) how they are underſtood to be given to the <hi>Church.</hi> Whether 1. <hi>Objectivè,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Objectivè.</hi>
                  </note> that the Church is the <hi>object</hi> of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of the Keys, that is, they are given for the good and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Church: Or 2. <hi>Subjectivè,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Subjectivè.</hi>
                  </note> that the Church is the <hi>Subject</hi> Recipient, to imploy and exerciſe the Keys: and this, either <hi>immediatly</hi> by her ſelf, in whole, or in part, without Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers: or <hi>mediatly</hi> by her Officers: that is, whether the Church be the next and firſt ſubject of the Keys, to convey them, or any part of them to her Officers; Or that ſhe is ſaid to be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40476:4"/> the <hi>remote ſubject,</hi> as including the Officers, to whom prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily and immediatly Chriſt hath committed the Keys for the good of the Church; as <hi>ſight</hi> is immediatly intruſted with the <hi>eyes,</hi> for the good and benefit of the whole body. And if it ſhould happen that any power of the Keys ſhould appear to be given to the Church as diſtinct from her Officers; whether it belong firſt to the <hi>Catholike viſible Church,</hi> or to a <hi>particular</hi> Congregation. The Queſtion then is clearly this <q>[Whether the Keys of the Kingdom of heaven be given <hi>ſubjectivè</hi> to the Church-Catholike in her Officers, on the particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation without (or with) her Officers.]</q>
               </p>
               <p>And now we ſhall conſider what you <hi>reſolve,</hi> upon this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; Thus you aſſert. <q>[The Church to which the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus committed the Keyes of the Kingdom of Heaven, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.29. is <hi>caetus Fidelium,</hi> commonly called a particular viſible Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> To which I anſwered (not as an <hi>Avenger,</hi> there is not the leaſt colour of that, but as an <hi>Aſſertor,</hi> giving alſo my reaſons) Of all the reſt, this is the moſt <hi>improbable</hi> ſenſe of our Saviours words, if by the <hi>Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> on earth, he meaneth that Church of which he ſpake in <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. But that was either the <hi>Catholike</hi> viſible Church; or rather the <hi>Inviſible myſticall</hi> Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That one, or both of theſe (for by my word <hi>rather,</hi> I do not exclude the other) is meant, and that pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily, is to me ſtill moſt probable; upon theſe reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. This being the firſt time, that the Church (<hi>my Church,</hi> the <hi>evangelical</hi> Church is named, it is not probable, that our Saviour, would intend it onely of a <hi>particular</hi> Congregation, but of the <hi>Catholike Church;</hi> for that is primarily Chriſts <hi>Church,</hi> and that is properly built upon the <hi>rock;</hi> and againſt that the gates of hell ſhall never prevail; whereas, (as I ſay afterwards) <hi>particular Churches</hi> may fail, and have failed. There is farre more colour for a <hi>particular Church</hi> to be meant. <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.17. <hi>Tell the Church:</hi> becauſe <hi>excommunication</hi> is executed in a particular Church firſt, and <hi>conſequently</hi> in the <hi>Catholike Church:</hi> but there is not any <hi>ſhadow</hi> for it in the text in hand. Did Chriſt mean, I will build my <hi>Church,</hi> that is, a <hi>particular Church</hi> one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, upon this rock, and not rather the <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> and the particular ſecondarily, as a <hi>member</hi> thereof? It may be a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40476:5"/> queſtion between the <hi>Inviſible,</hi> and <hi>Viſible</hi> Catholike Church, which is meant there, (as after,) but none, till of late, ſo much as made the queſtion, betwixt the <hi>Catholike</hi> and <hi>particular</hi> Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Peter,</hi> was an Apoſtle, and had given to him the <hi>Keyes</hi> of the <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> not of any <hi>particular Church;</hi> for he (and ſo his fellow-Apoſtles) were never <hi>Pastors</hi> of any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church: therefore, it ſeems more reaſonable, that the <hi>Catholike Church</hi> is there meant. They had <hi>habitually</hi> the <hi>Keyes</hi> of particular Churches, in the Catholike; as Paſtors have habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually the Keyes of the <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> in a particular: They were <hi>actually</hi> Elders of the whole Church; as <hi>Paſtors</hi> are <hi>actually</hi> Elders of a particular Church.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Keyes</hi> of the Kingdom of Heaven, that is, the <hi>Church,</hi> are given to <hi>Peter,</hi> as diſtinguiſhed from the <hi>Church,</hi> therefore they are not there given to the <hi>Church.</hi> As if a <hi>Lord</hi> ſhould ſay to him whom he conſtitutes his <hi>Steward,</hi> I give to thee the <hi>Keyes</hi> of the Family, to open and ſhut the doors of the Houſe; could the ſervants, or children, or any for them, conclude from this grant, the <hi>Keyes</hi> were given to the Family? was <hi>Peter</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> to whom the <hi>Keyes</hi> of the Church were given? And therefore, as <hi>diſtruſting</hi> this ſenſe of this Scripture, you ſay, (as you had ſaid of the other Apoſtles and Elders) <q>[The Church or Congregation of profeſſed believers received that portion al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of Church-power,<note place="margin">The Keys pag. 5.</note> which belonged unto them, if not there, (that is, in this text in hand) yet elſewhere.]</q> Not here for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; whether elſewhere or no, ſhall be tried hereafter. It is not a <hi>reaſonable conſtruction</hi> of this text, to ſay, I give to thee the <hi>Keyes</hi> of the Kingdom of Heaven, that is, of the <hi>Church:</hi> and to mean, I give to the <hi>Church,</hi> the <hi>Keyes</hi> of the Church. I ſaid therefore, (and I think truly,) that of all the reſt this is the moſt <hi>improbable</hi> ſenſe of our Saviours words; that it is a <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular</hi> Church, to which the <hi>Keyes</hi> were given, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.19. It muſt then be taken of the <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> either Inviſible, or Viſible, or none.</p>
               <p>But you are pleaſed to take away the <hi>ſubject</hi> of this queſtion, denying any <hi>Catholike viſible Church:</hi> 
                  <q>[For (ſay you) I do not read, that the Scripture any where, acknowledges a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40476:5"/> viſible Church at all.]</q> It is ſuppoſed by very Judicious <hi>Divines,</hi> that you may read of it often in Scripture, and in this place for one. It cannot be denied, but the Church, is often put for the whole multitude of beleevers, whether in truth, or in ſhew only: <hi>Acts</hi> 8.3. <hi>Saul</hi> made havock of the Church: and <hi>Acts</hi> 12.1. &amp;c. It was not any <hi>particular</hi> Church, but any of any <hi>Churches,</hi> any of that way, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.2. which muſt needs ſignifie the Church <hi>indefinetely</hi> as oppoſed to the <hi>world,</hi> not any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church: Nor was it the <hi>Catholike Inviſible</hi> Church that they perſecuted, as ſuch; for they could not <hi>know</hi> them to be ſuch: Therefore it muſt be the <hi>Catholike Viſible Church.</hi> Beſides, your ſelf unawares confeſſe it, in the following words; <q>[Though the whole Church, (or which is all one, the Catholike Church) may be viſible, in her ſingular members, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> Is not this to confeſſe a Catholike viſible Church? But (ſay you) <q>[So they are not a Church: or though it may be viſible in the ſeverall particular Congregations, yet none of them is Catholike.]</q> I hope you do not imagine, that any is <hi>ſo ſimple,</hi> to think that the <hi>whole Church</hi> can be ſeen at once; D. <hi>A.</hi> ſaid well, <hi>Eccleſia non eſt tota ſimul viſibilis:</hi> The Church (he means the <hi>Catholike Church</hi>) is not all viſible at once or at one view: then it were more then <hi>viſibilis,</hi> even <hi>viſa:</hi> not viſible ſo much as ſeen; I know you obſerve the difference: :But if the whole Church be <hi>viſible</hi> in her members, whether in the particular perſons, or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Congregations, is not the whole <hi>viſible,</hi> though not <hi>viſa,</hi> ſeen at once? No more is the <hi>whole world</hi> viſible, but in its parts, yet the world is viſible: No more is a <hi>Congregation</hi> of many perſons viſible, that is, ſeen at once; yet you will not ſay but the <hi>whole</hi> is viſible. True, but then <hi>none</hi> of thoſe particular Congregations are Catholike. <q>[The Catholike Church, is not viſible as a Church, and the Church that is viſible, is not Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike.]</q> But 1. If there be a <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> (which you ſuppoſe here in theſe words.) 2. If that <hi>Church</hi> be viſible in its <hi>parts,</hi> the ſingular members, which you alſo grant. 3. If the <hi>particular</hi> Congregations, as parts, be alſo viſible, as <hi>Churches.</hi> 4. If the <hi>whole Church</hi> be made up of choſe particular Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es which are viſible: muſt not the <hi>whole,</hi> or (which is all one) the <hi>Catholike Church</hi> be viſible? and then the whole Church that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40476:6"/> is viſible, in its parts, is alſo Catholike: and the <hi>Catholike Church</hi> is viſible in its parts: And is it not then true, that there is a <hi>Catholike viſible Church?</hi> It might be added, that a <hi>particular</hi> Church, is not <hi>viſible</hi> as a Church; but as a company of men aſſembled; for the <hi>form</hi> of the Church (which you ſay is the Covenant) is not viſible. And once more you ſeem to yeeld the <hi>Catholike viſible</hi> Church, when you ſay, <q>[Though all of them (the particular Congregations) may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Catholike Church, or generall Aſſembly, if they were met together.]</q> Only you adde, <q>[Yet I would be loth to ſay, that Chriſt giveth the power of the Keys (all Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call power into their hands.]</q> I ſhould indeed be loth to ſay ſo; for I do not yet believe, that our Saviour in that Text did give the <hi>power</hi> of the Keys to the Church at all, whether parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular or Catholike, but to <hi>Peter,</hi> to the Officers for the Church. <hi>To thee</hi> (Peter) <hi>I give the Keys of the Church.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Yet the queſtion upon that Text is not reſolved; whether by <hi>Church</hi> is meant the <hi>Catholike viſible</hi> or <hi>inviſible Church</hi>] ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is not to be taken for a <hi>particular Church</hi>] And to this you ſay, That I <q>[diſtruſting the meaning to be of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like viſible Church, expound it rather to be meant of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible myſticall Church]</q> But 1. By my word <hi>[rather]</hi> I did not exclude the <hi>Catholike viſible</hi> Church: though I was ſway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the reaſon annexed, to incline to that ſenſe; Becauſe that Church only is <hi>built on the rock,</hi> and againſt that, the gates of hell ſhall never prevail, whereas particular Churches may fail. And I am not alone in this Expoſition. 2. <hi>Viſible</hi> and <hi>inviſible,</hi> do not <hi>ſpecifically</hi> difference Churches, but are (as your ſelf ſay, ſomewhere) but <hi>adjuncts</hi> of the ſame Church: whereupon it may be true of both, that, by the <hi>Kingdom of heaven,</hi> that is, the <hi>Church,</hi> ver. 18. may be meant both theſe, as included in the ſame Church: the <hi>inviſible</hi> in the <hi>viſible:</hi> But of which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour underſtood it, is worth enquiry: Upon ſecond thoughts (not excluding the <hi>inviſible</hi>) I encline now to think he meant is of the <hi>Catholike viſible</hi> Church. The Reverend M. <hi>Hooker</hi> confeſſes himſelf inclined that way, by ſome paſſages of M. <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therford,</hi> to take it of the viſible Church; (though he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a <hi>Catholike</hi> viſible Church, as well as you) by the force and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40476:6"/> conviction of this Argument. <q>[That Church is here meant, which is built upon the Rock Chriſt, by the viſible confeſſion of <hi>Peter;</hi> But the inviſible Church is not built by a viſible profeſſion, ſuch as <hi>Peters</hi> was: The propoſition is made good by the meaning of the words: Thou haſt made a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of my ſelf a rock, and upon my ſelf ſo confeſſed, will I build my Church.]</q> I muſt ingeniouſly confeſſe, I am not convinced by this argument. For the <hi>Inviſible Church</hi> is alſo built upon that rock by a <hi>viſible profeſſion,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Peters</hi> was: The inviſible Church is the ſame Church, or the ſame members, with the viſible; and are all built upon the ſame rock by the ſame profeſſion of faith; True beleevers and falſe make the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of faith, and the <hi>Elect</hi> are viſible members of the Church, though as they are <hi>elect</hi> they are inviſible: viſible and inviſible are in themſelves oppoſite, but not in ſeveral reſpects, they may predicated of the ſame ſubject; That which I obſerve from him is this, he acknowledgeth and argues, that the <hi>viſible Church</hi> is here meant: the queſtion is whether the Catholike or particular viſible Church is there intended: For the <hi>Catholike viſible</hi> much hath been ſaid already; and now I adde from his confeſſion; <q>[Upon my ſelf ſo confeſſed, will I build my Church.]</q> what? only a particular Church, and not rather the whole Church? yea, rather the latter; for the reaſon objected againſt the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church; becauſe againſt the viſible <hi>Church</hi> particular the gates of hell have prevailed: he anſwers, <q>[The viſible Church is attended in a double reſpect:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ibid</hi> p. 2. 7.</note> either as this or that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Congregation, or elſe as a Church univerſall, exiſting in the particulars: and in this latter ſenſe it is taken in this place, and then it is a ſure and confeſſed truth, That the viſible Church doth not fail.]</q> If now it be taken in the latter ſenſe in this place, for the <hi>Church univerſall,</hi> exiſting in the particulars, then it is meant of the <hi>Catholike viſible</hi> Church, not of a particular viſible Church. See more in M. <hi>Hookers</hi> Survey p. 217. If I may now declare my judgement, take it thus: Upon this rock, that is, my ſelf thus confeſſed, or this confeſſion of my ſelf, <q>[To be the Chriſt the Son of the living God.]</q> will I build my <hi>(Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gellicall)</hi> Church: The Church before Chriſts coming was built upon the ſame foundation, with this difference, They profeſſed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40476:7"/> the Meſſiah to come, The ſeed of the woman to break the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents head, was the <hi>foundation</hi> of their faith from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, till <hi>Abrahams</hi> time: After that, this was laid as the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation <q>[<hi>In thy ſeed ſhall all the nations be bleſſed,</hi> &amp;c.]</q> But the Chriſtian or Evangelical Church is built upon this Goſpel-foundation or Truth Truth <q>[That this particular perſon Jeſus Chriſt is the Sonne of God, and that Meſſiah which was to come.]</q> So the woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> Joh. 4.29. <hi>Is not this the Chriſt?</hi> and verſ. 42. <q>["We know that this is indeed the Chriſt, the Saviour of the world.]</q> 
                  <hi>In like manner the Eunuch,</hi> Act. <hi>8.37.</hi> 
                  <q>["If thou beleeveſt, thou mayſt; And he anſwered, and ſaid, I beleeve that Jeſus Christ is the Son of God.]</q> And upon this rock, or Jeſus Chriſt, ſo confeſſed, was every particular<note n="*" place="margin">Women alſo as well as men.</note> member con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, built, and conſequently the Church: What Church? a particular Congregation? yes, ſecondarily, as a part of the whole viſible Church, but primarily, the whole Church of the New Teſtament, and that I take to be eſpecially the ſenſe of the word <hi>Church,</hi> in this Text, though (as I ſaid) not excluding the <hi>Inviſible</hi> Church.</p>
               <p>And herein your ſelf ſeem to agree with me, when you ſay, <q>[Indeed true it is, that <hi>Peter</hi> and other Preachers of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel have received ſuch a power of the Keys, to open to belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers a door into the inviſible Church, <hi>&amp;c</hi>]</q> But then, the inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church cannot be excluded from one part of the meaning of the kingdom of heaven, whereof <hi>Peter</hi> received the Keys: and conſequently the <hi>Church</hi> to which the Lord Jeſus committed the Keys of the Kingdom of heaven, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.19. is not only <hi>caetus fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delium,</hi> commonly called a particular Church (if at all) which was your aſſertion. And once more, it may be ſaid, that the <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible</hi> Catholike Church cannot be excluded from one part of the meaning of the Kingdom of heaven, in that Text, for the reaſon which you give alſo; Becauſe there is a <hi>power</hi> of the Keys to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen a door to profeſt beleevers, into the <hi>Catholike viſible</hi> Church, as well as into a <hi>particular</hi> viſible Church. But be it meant of the <hi>inviſible</hi> or <hi>viſible</hi> Catholike Church, or of a <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular</hi> viſible Church, it's manifeſt, that in this Text the Keys are not given to the Church; but the Keys of the Church are given to <hi>Peter,</hi> contra-diſtinguiſhed, as an Officer, from the Church.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:40476:7"/>
               <p>But you object, <q>[Certain it is, that when by the power of the Keys a beleever is received into the inviſible Church, he can never be ſhut again out of that Church: but the Keys here given to <hi>Peter,</hi> have power to ſhut out of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of heaven even the ſame perſons: And therefore the the Kingdom of heaven is not meant only of the inviſible Church.]</q> I pray Sir, ſhould not your concluſion be from thoſe premiſes <q>[Therefore the Kingdom of heaven is not meant at all of the inviſible Church:]</q> which yet you have aſſerted, to be part of the meaning:And did you not from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſay, that by was meant the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of grace and glory: And doth not the Text ſay, that <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> hath keys given him, as well to ſhut out the Kingdom of heavens, as open the door thereof? <q>[Whatſoever thou ſhalt binde on earth, ſhall be bound in heaven:</q> If ſo; then your propoſition is not true, That a beleever received into the <hi>Inviſible</hi> Church, can never be ſent again out of that Church: Your ſelf ſay, a little below, <hi>pag.</hi> 8. of this ſecond part. <q>[It may truly be ſaid, whoſoever is bound or looſed in any one particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Church, is alſo bound in the Kingdom of glory ]</q> and is not that, as much as to be <hi>ſhut out</hi> of the <hi>Inviſible</hi> Church? You cannot but know, that the judgment of Divines is, that if a <hi>true beleever,</hi> be excommunicated, for ſome crime, he is for a time <hi>ſuſpended</hi> from the Kingdom of Heaven,<note place="margin">See M. <hi>Hookers</hi> Survey part. 1. p. 204. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct. Viſible Saints.</note> and ſo in a ſenſe put out of the <hi>Inviſible</hi> Church; and if it were poſſible for him to die unrepenting, he might periſh; and the <hi>text</hi> it ſelf ſeems to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie it, when it ſayes, <q>[whatſoever is bound on earth, ſhall be bound in heaven]</q>
               </p>
               <p>And now ſhall conſider what you ſay to the <hi>reaſons</hi> for my <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>1</label> Aſſertion; The firſt was, becauſe that Church, there meant, was built upon the rock, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To which you anſwer; <q>[It is not true that the Inviſible Church onely, built upon a rock. For particular Churches are built upon a rock alſo: built they are upon Divine Inſtitution, and Chriſt is laid for the foundation of them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> Before I anſwer, I muſt diſtinguiſh of thoſe words <hi>[built upon a rock;]</hi> which not obſerved, cauſe confuſion in this preſent buſineſſe: Two things are here enquirable: 1. What is meant by the <hi>Rock?</hi> It may be taken 1. For <hi>Chriſt</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:40476:8"/> himſelf, the tried and ſure <hi>foundation,</hi> (as he is elſwhere called,) and ſo it may be underſtood, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.24. <hi>[built his houſe upon a rock,]</hi> oppoſed there to the <hi>ſand.</hi> 2. For <hi>Chriſt confeſſed</hi> to be the Sonne of God, and the <hi>Meſſiah;</hi> as he was by <hi>Peter</hi> profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be; [upon my ſelf ſo confeſſed, will I build my <hi>Church</hi>] as Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> expoundeth it above. 2. What it is to be <hi>built</hi> upon the rock?<note place="margin">Vide D. <hi>Ameſ. Medul.</hi> lib. 1. c. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. ſ. 11.</note> It is, either by <hi>internall union,</hi> with Chriſt, as the rock and foundation; or by <hi>externall profeſſion;</hi> as your ſelf inſinuate to me the diſtinction, <hi>pag.</hi> 7. when you ſay, <q>[if they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate, they were never founded upon Chriſt, but in an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward form.]</q> And now, I ſhall ingeniouſly acknowledge my ſelf not <hi>diſtinct</hi> enough, when I ſaid, <q>[It is the Inviſible Church, which is built upon the rock, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> and do confeſſe my ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden to Mr. <hi>Ruth.</hi> and Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> for this light; and now ſee, that the <hi>viſible Church</hi> alſo, is built upon the rock. Onely I dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> in this, that be by <hi>viſible Church,</hi> means on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, a particular Church, but I, the <hi>Catholike viſible</hi> Church, as was diſcourſed above. But now, upon the former diſtinctions. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That if you take the <hi>Rock</hi> for Chriſt himſelf, and the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on him,<note place="margin">See <hi>part.</hi> 2. <hi>pa,</hi> 24. your own words, <hi>It is readily,</hi> &amp;c.</note> for <hi>Internall</hi> union with him; then the <hi>Inviſible</hi> Church onely, is built upon the <hi>rock,</hi> and againſt that the gates of hell ſhall never prevail. But if you underſtand the <hi>Rock,</hi> to be that <hi>confeſſion</hi> of <hi>Peter,</hi> or rather <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſo confeſſed, as he was by <hi>Peter;</hi> and the building on that <hi>foundation,</hi> for an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal profeſſion, or (in your words) in an <hi>outward form:</hi> Then I ſay, the <hi>viſible</hi> Church is ſo founded upon the rock: But then I adde, that it muſt not be reſtrained to a <hi>particular</hi> Church (againſt which the gates of hell have prevailed, which contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts our Saviours promiſe) but declared to the <hi>Catholike vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible</hi> Church (exiſting in the particulars, as M. <hi>Hooker</hi> ſaid) againſt which the <hi>gates of hell</hi> (what ever they be) ſhall never prevail. And now I conſider what you ſay, <q>[It is not true, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for particular Churches are built upon a rock alſo:]</q> But then Sir, I pray, how will you (without a diſtinction) anſwer the Text, which ſayes, the <hi>gates of hell</hi> ſhall never prevail againſt that Church which is built on the rock? You ſay <q>[Built they are upon divine inſtitution, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> But I ſuppoſe you do but <hi>elude</hi> and not anſwer here: Is it all one to be built upon
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40476:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> the <hi>rock,</hi> and upon divine <hi>inſtitution?</hi> Then particular Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es ſhould not fail: for thoſe that are built upon a <hi>rock</hi> ſhall never fail: Particular Churches are built upon a rock alſo; True, ſo far as they are true beleevers: Others of them are expreſly ſaid to be built upon the <hi>ſand;</hi> yet are they built upon <hi>Chriſts inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution:</hi> Suppoſe a <hi>particular</hi> Church, conſiſting of all <hi>hypocrites,</hi> (it's poſſible to be ſo) having all externall Ordinances; will you ſay, thoſe are built upon the rock Chriſt? or will you ſay, they are no Churches of Chriſt, becauſe they are not built upon Chriſt as a rock or foundation? Neither of theſe can you ſay, not the latter, for they are built upon the <hi>Inſtitution</hi> of Chriſt not the former, for hypocrites have not Chriſt for their founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but are built upon the ſand. Hear your own words, <hi>pag.</hi> 40. <q>[If the profeſſion of the doctrine of faith be true, though the grace of faith in the profeſſour be uncertain, and may be hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriticall, and ſo falſe, yet we dare not deny the nature and power of a Church to ſuch.]</q> But ſay I again, ſuch are not founded upon the <hi>rock</hi> Chriſt, though they be upon his <hi>Institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> Therefore <hi>Inſtitution</hi> and <hi>rock,</hi> are not both one. But you confute your ſelf, when you ſay <q>[Chriſt is not the head of that Church, whereof he is not the foundation, and where he is the foundation, he is alſo the rock:]</q> Now (ſay I) Chriſt is not the head of hypocrites, therefore not the <hi>foundation,</hi> nor the <hi>rock</hi> for (as you adde) Chriſt is not a <hi>ſandy foundation:</hi> yet are they built upon the <hi>Inſtitution</hi> of Chriſt; and may and do fail, which they could not if they were built upon Chriſt a rock: But ſay you <q>[What then? ſo may the true diſciples of Chriſt fail (in reſpect of bodily ſubſiſtence) and yet the gates of hell never prevail againſt them,]</q> Did Chriſt mean in regard of bodily <hi>ſubſiſtence,</hi> that the gates of hell ſhould not prevail againſt the Church? Do not ſome particular Churches fail in regard of the truth it ſelf, and the gates of hell prevail againſt the ſouls of all their members? yet Chriſt ſayes, they ſhall not prevail againſt the Church built upon the rock. Or rather did he not mean it of the <hi>Catholike viſible</hi> Church, in this ſenſe; that he will ever have a Church in one place or other? yes, ſay you <q>[God may remove the Candleſtick, that is, his particular Church, yet he will have ever ſome or other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40476:9"/> Churches viſible, in one place or other.]</q> That is, ſay I, God will have ever a Catholike viſible Church, exiſting in the particulars: and ſo (ſayes M. <hi>Hooker</hi>) viſible Church doth nor fail. Yet you go on to ſay, <q>[Thoſe Churches that were founded upon Chriſt, and built upon that rock, neither failed nor fell away.]</q> But (I aſſume) thoſe Churches that were founded upon his <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> fell away and failed, therefore they were not built upon the rock. You adde again <q>[If the poſterity of a holy Church do degenerate, they were never founded upon Chriſt, but in an outward form]</q> True, ſay I, yet they as well as their predeceſſors were built upon Chriſts <hi>Inſtitution.</hi> Therefore to be built upon divine <hi>Inſtitution</hi> meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, is not the ſame, as to be built on a <hi>rock:</hi> And ſo you have <hi>eluded,</hi> not anſwered the argument.</p>
               <p>I have but one thing more to ſay to your Teſtimonies from M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Whit. Junius,</hi> and <hi>D. Ames:</hi> You ſay, <q>[They diſpute Catholike viſible Church, but maintain the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church to be inviſible]</q> But 1. The Church Catholike of I which thoſe Divines ſpeak, againſt Papiſts, is not the ſame with ours in this Diſpute: They intend it of the Church of the Elect, of all ages and times, which is the Catholike Church mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Creed, as the object of our faith, not of our ſenſe: but we take it in the ſecond ſenſe delivered in the beginning, for the whole multitude of beleevers, or profeſſours of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel in all places of the world at once; And the parts of this Church whether particular members or particular Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons being viſible, the whole (or which is all one, the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church) muſt needs be viſible.<note place="margin">D. <hi>Ameſ. Med.</hi> lib. 1. cap. 31. ſect. 7. cap. 32. ſect. 1.</note> And D. <hi>Ames</hi> by name, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving defined this Church to be <hi>Caetus hominum vocatorum, fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium, vel caetus eorum qui ſunt in Chriſto,</hi> &amp;c, Of this ſame Church (which cannot be only the particular Church, he ſaies, it is <hi>viſibilis in ſuis partibus:</hi> and in the former chapter, <hi>Sect.</hi> laſt, <hi>Eccleſia nunquam planè deſinit eſſe viſibilis:</hi> The Church Catholike (of that he ſpake) never wholly ceaſeth to be vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible. 2. The Catholike Church which they diſpute againſt, is in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> ſenſe, a Catholike <hi>Romane</hi> Church, animated by the Pope as an head, and by Catholike Officers actually, in a ſubordination, as a <hi>Politicall</hi> body: But this we deny as well
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40476:9"/> as they. We take it only for the whole <hi>multitude</hi> of beleevers, diſtinguiſhed into ſeverall Congregations, which all make up <hi>one body,</hi> whereof Chriſt alone is the <hi>Head.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Survey <hi>part.</hi> 1. pag. 15, 16. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> which Chriſt is an Head by poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> We ſhall take it in M. <hi>Hookers</hi> words, <q>[The Church is the viſible kingdom of Chriſt, in which he reigns by the Scepter of his Word and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and execution of diſcipline,]</q> which viſible kingdom of Chriſt, is the <hi>whole Church,</hi> or (which is all one) the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church, viſible in her members.</p>
               <p>And now I come to my ſecond Reaſon, or (as you call it) <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>2</label> Objection, The kingdom of glory (one part of the meaning of the Kingdom of heaven, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.19.) is not <hi>contra-diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed</hi> to a particular Congregation, but to the <hi>generall</hi> viſible Church on earth. You anſwer 1. <q>[There is not any particular Church on earth, but may be, upon juſt occaſion contra-di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed from the kingdom of glory]</q> It may be ſo, but very <hi>improperly,</hi> and with reſpect to the <hi>whole Church</hi> on earth: But what's this to the Text or Objection? The queſtion is not, what may be elſewhere, but what is the meaning in this Text: It ſaies not, whatever thou ſhalt binde in a <hi>particular Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> but in earth, that is, the <hi>viſible Church</hi> on earth, as contra-diſtinguiſhed to the <hi>world</hi> here,<note place="margin">See the Keys pag. 2. ſ. 1.</note> and the kingdom of glory a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove: And beſides, he that is bound in any particular Church, is bound in all the Churches on earth; and ſo the diſtinction of heaven and earth reſpects the whole Church, rather then any particular Church. 2. And this your ſecond Anſwer implies, <q>[You did not, mean it in any one ſingle Congregation on earth, but generally and indefinitely in every particular Church on earth; for every Apoſtle had tranſcendent power in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular Church on earth.]</q> But 1. why may you not ſay as well ["generally in the whole Catholike Church on earth.] ſeeing <hi>Peter</hi> received power to binde and looſe, in the <hi>whole Church</hi> primarily (being an Apoſtle) and ſecondarily in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Congregations? 2. If <hi>Peter</hi> as an Apoſtle received ſuch power in the <hi>whole Church,</hi> what is that to <hi>Elders</hi> and <hi>Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers;</hi> to challenge power of the <hi>Keys</hi> from this Text, in all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Congregations? Sure, they have not <hi>tranſcendent power</hi> indefinitely, much leſſe generally, in every particular Church on earth. 3. How did <hi>Peter</hi> receive the Keys in every particular
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40476:10"/> Church indefinitely? As an Apoſtle, or as an Elder, or as a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever? Not as an Apoſtle or Elder; that you denied in the way? Not as a Beleever, for if they have any power in the Keys, it is in the particular Congregation. Whence I conclude, by <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of heaven</hi> there, is not meant a particular, but the <hi>Catholike viſible</hi> Church, as contra-diſtinguiſhed to the Kingdome of glory.</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>3,</label> That Church is meant (ſaid I) whereof <hi>Peter</hi> was one, but <hi>Peter</hi> was not a member of a particular Congregation; for there was none ſuch then extant. You are pleaſed to jeer me with your Logick; and tell me <q>[there is a fallacy in ſuch ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing, to be left to Sophiſters, or uſed, when I will refreſh my wit with young ſcholars:]</q> But I pray Sir, where lies the fallacy? The major is your own, the minor cannot be denied; <hi>Peter</hi> was not a member of a particular Congregation. The proof of this laſt Propoſition is, becauſe there was none extant at that time: This is alſo true, and partly confeſſed by your ſelf, where then lies the fallacy? <q>[The <hi>Copula</hi> doth conno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate; Time, which it ought not to do, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> You inſtance in a <hi>Sophiſm;</hi> fit indeed for young ſcholars: But nothing parallel to my arguing: And your other Argument from <hi>reſurrection</hi> is far wide: you ſay <q>[The Propoſition is true, becauſe the ſubject and praedicate have true connexion in the nature of the thing though not in the preſent order of time.]</q> But ſo it is not in my arguing; For <hi>Peter</hi> was not at any time a member of a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Congregation, neither then nor afterwards: There was then no fallacy or ſophiſm in my arguing; The weakneſſe was in the proof; For whereas I ſaid, <hi>Peter</hi> was not a member of a particular Congregation, becauſe there was none extant at that time; I ſhould have ſaid, <hi>Peter,</hi> being an Apoſtle, was never a member of a particular Congregation; Therefore the Church there mean could not be a particular Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>4</label> I ſaid Fourthly, That Church whereof <hi>Peter</hi> received the <hi>Keys,</hi> was ſuch, whereto an offended brother might tell an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and have it cenſured; but that was never done in a Church of Saints, without Officers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                  <q>[This (ſay you) is another paſſage of Sophiſtry: Here are <hi>quatuor termini</hi> in this
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40476:10"/> Syllogiſm: might tell an offence, and did tell an offence, make two different <hi>Mediums.</hi>]</q> Make you the Syllogiſm right as you would have it; you make the minor thus, <q>[But the Church of Saints without Officers was not ſuch, to whom an offended brother might tell an offence, and have it cenſured.]</q> And this you deny. But I ſhall prove it thus. 1. From the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your brethren here, who ſay, <q>[The brethren cannot proceed to any publike cenſures without Officers:]</q> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is to no purpoſe to tell an offence to a <hi>Church</hi> of belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers without Officers. 2. From your ſelf, who expreſly ſay: <q>[Excommunication is one of the higheſt Acts of Rule, and therefore cannot be performed, but by ſome Rulers:<note place="margin">The Keys pag. 16.</note>]</q> though I confeſſe, you flatly contradict your ſelf in the <hi>way,</hi> pag. 101. And now my Syllogiſm may eaſily be defended and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from a Sophiſm, by adding the minor more explicitly, thus, <q>[But a Church of Saints without Officers, is not ſuch a Church:]</q> This is proved by what I ſay, That was never done in a Church of Saints, without Officers; that is, no example can be brought from Scripture or Hiſtory, of ſuch a practice, where a Church of Saints without Officers did cenſure an offence; Therefore the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> (which you inſtance in) was not ſuch a Church, for it had Officers, who (as I ſaid) might <hi>authoritatively</hi> cenſure offenders. <q>[What of that? (ſay you) if a Church of Saints without Officers, have power from Chriſt to elect Officers, then alſo to admit members; And if to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit without Officers, then to exclude them without Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers:]</q> Surely, whatever mine was, this is a fallacy and a Sophiſm, called <hi>petitio principij:</hi> For you know, we deny, that a Church of Saints without Officers, have power to <hi>elect,</hi> that is, ordain and make Officers, and you ought not to beg it. And what mean you by <hi>power</hi> to admit members? Admiſſion of members is either at their <hi>firſt converſion,</hi> which is done by bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and ſo your ſelf ſay, None but Officers can admit, for none but Officers can <hi>baptize;</hi> or it is at the removall of a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber from one Church to another, to admit into the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of another Church; but this, either is no part of the <hi>power</hi> of the Keys, or if it be, it belongs to a <hi>Church</hi> with Officers. Nay, your argument will recoil upon your ſelf, It is the ſame
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40476:11"/> 
                  <hi>power</hi> to open and ſhut, to admit and exclude; But a <hi>Church</hi> of Saints without Officers cannot exclude or ſhut out, therefore nor can they admit or open. The <hi>minor</hi> is your own a little above, and your brethrens alſo: <q>[<hi>Excommunication</hi> being an Act of Rule, cannot be performed but by ſome Rulers.]</q>
               </p>
               <p>And here I deſire you to take notice, That a great g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ound of your miſtakes, lies in the <hi>miſapplication</hi> or <hi>attribution</hi> of the <hi>power</hi> of the Keys to the brethren, to elect, that is, to make and ordain their own Officers; making election the principall, and ordination but a circumſtance or ſolemnity, not neceſſary by the <hi>Inſtitution</hi> of Chriſt, to belong to the Officers. Indeed, it ſeems to follow rationally, They that may <hi>ordain</hi> their own <hi>Officers,</hi> may <hi>de-ordain them,</hi> or caſt them out; for it is the ſame power <hi>instituere &amp; deſtituere,</hi> as you ſay: And then if the brethren may ordain and de-ordain their Officers, much more may they admit or exclude members. But me thinks the <hi>Antecedent</hi> is to be denied, and we prove it thus: They that may ordain Officers to ſuch employments, may in caſe of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity at leaſt formally themſelves perform them: But you conſtantly deny,<note place="margin">The Way, pag. 44. and then par 2. p. 3. Par. 2. pag. 33.</note> that any but Officers can adminiſter Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: The major is alſo your own Aſſertion, in this laſt book of yours thus you ſpeak <q>[I confeſſe, I do not well underſtand how a man in caſe of neceſſity hath any virtuall power to this or that Act, but he hath alſo a formall power to do ſuch an Act in that caſe of Neceſſity.]</q> But (I aſſume) the brethren in a caſe of Neceſſity (ſay you) have a virtuall power to <hi>ordain</hi> their Officers, who can doe thoſe Acts, adminiſter Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> therefore in that Neceſſity, when they have no Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, they have a formal power to adminiſter Sacraments. Nor can I ſee any reaſon why thoſe that may ordain Officers, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter cenſures without Officers, may not alſo adminiſter Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments. For to adminiſter Sacraments is one of the <hi>loweſt acts</hi> of a Miniſter, certainly leſſe then preaching <q>[Chriſt ſent me not to baptize but to preach the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Par. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. pag. 81.</note>]</q> 
                  <hi>q. d.</hi> that was the chiefeſt part of his errand, ſaies M. <hi>Hooker.</hi> And Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation (and ſo admiſſion of Officers by Election) is one of the <hi>higheſt acts</hi> of Rule, (ſay you:) But you allow your brethren to preach, and to elect, and caſt out <hi>Officers;</hi> therefore they may
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40476:11"/> as well if not better be allowed to adminiſter Sacraments; which yet you do deny. How <hi>Independent</hi> indeed is your way? how <hi>inconſiſtent</hi> your doctrines? I wiſh you would at laſt conſider it. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>5</label> 
               </p>
               <p>I ſaid in the fifth place, The <hi>Church</hi> to which the <hi>Keys</hi> are given, are ſaid (by you) to be ſuch as do all of them meet in one place, for the adminiſtration of the Ordinances of Chriſt. But the Ordinances of Chriſt are not to be found, much leſſe admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred in a Church of beleevers without Officers: Therefore. To this you anſwer thus, <q>[The truth is, though the Ordinances may not all of them be adminiſtred in a Church of beleevers without Officers, as authoritative diſpenſing of the Word and cenſures, and miniſtration of Sacraments: yet ſome Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances may be found and adminiſtred there:]</q> But Sir, 1. Did not you intend it of all Ordinances, that they may and muſt be adminiſtred in a Church of beleevers? Did you not define a <hi>Church</hi> to be a company of beleevers met together to enjoy all Ordinances? 2. I ſaid (all) the Ordinances are not to be found in a Church of beleevers without Officers, you firſt take no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of that, but ſay, <hi>though all may not be administred there:</hi> and then confeſſe, <hi>Some of them cannot be found</hi> and adminiſtred there: Surely thoſe that cannot be found there (as ſome can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not) cannot be adminiſtred there: But (ſay I) in that Church to which the <hi>Keys</hi> were given, all Ordinances (which are the <hi>Keys</hi>) may be found and adminiſtred. Therefore that Church and yours are not the ſame: 3. What are thoſe <hi>Some Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances</hi> which may be found there? <q>[1. Two or three to meet together, and pray, and admoniſh one another, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> But are two or three a Church? You ſay ſomewhere 7. are the leaſt number. And may not any two or three beleevers, not in your <hi>Church-order,</hi> no members of any particular Church, meet and pray, <hi>&amp;c?</hi> have they then the power of the <hi>Keys?</hi> Is not reading of the word alſo an Ordinance of Chriſt, and ſinging of Pſalms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Are theſe alſo part of the power of the Keys? <q>[2. It is an Ordinance of Chriſt to elect Officers, for this is the power and priviledge of the Church of Brethren]</q> Let me uſe your own words to me in this paragraph <q>[This latter propoſition is left naked and unguarded without proof, and is but an <hi>ipſe dixit,</hi> &amp;c.]</q> for you know we deny it. And ſuppoſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40476:12"/> thoſe were Ordinances, and part of tho power of the Keys, yet they are not the Ordinances that I intended, <hi>viz.</hi> adminiſtration of Sacraments and cenſures; Theſe you have confeſſed (though you again deny it) are not to be found or adminiſtred in a <hi>Church</hi> without Officers;<note place="margin">They are not capable of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> S craments without Offi- p 20, there.</note> 
                  <q>[The truth is (your own words) the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Chriſt may not all of them be adminiſtred in a Church without Officer?, as authoritative diſpenſing of the word and cenſures, and miniſtration of Sacraments:]</q> what need I prove my latter propoſition when you confeſſe it? But you have an help for this: <q>[If a Church of beleevers may ſupply themſelves with Officers, when they want them (<hi>which you know we deny, unleſſe you mean they may procure them elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where)</hi> and if Officers and brethren have all ordinary Church-power <hi>(which we alſo deny to the brethren)</hi> and ſo all Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Chriſt, which are ordinarily adminiſtred, found there, then what hindereth, but that a Church of beleevers hath in it, as ſome Ordinances formally, ſo all radically and virtually, and the ſame adminiſtred, and adminiſtrable amongſt, them?</q>) This diſcourſe is a meer begging, of the queſtion firſt, and then a varying of it; A begging in that you take for grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the Brethren have a power in the Keys, eitheir formally or radically; and that becauſe they have a power to elect their own Officers; If by <hi>Election</hi> you mean the <hi>Creation</hi> or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Officers, we deny then any ſuch power: If you mean a <hi>deſignation</hi> or choice of a fit perſon, to be ordained by other Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, that is no <hi>power</hi> of the Keys; which your ſelf ſay <q>[are the Ordinances of Chriſt,<note place="margin">The Keys. p. 2.</note> as the preaching of the Word, and adminiſtring of the Seals and cenſures,]</q> You alſo <hi>vary</hi> the queſtion, by putting in two words; firſt, <hi>ordinarily administred,</hi> whenas I ſpake of all Ordinances ordinary, as thoſe mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or extraordinary, as <hi>Synods,</hi> which your ſelf acknowledge an Ordinance of God; and I think will not ſay it may be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in a particular Church of beleevers, without or with Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers. Secondly, You ſhuffle in another word <hi>Adminiſtrable</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them; whereas the queſtion was of Ordinances admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred; They are not all to be found, much leſſe adminiſtred in ſuch a Church: But all Ordinances, ordinary and extraordinary, are both adminiſtrable and adminiſtred in the Church, to which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40476:12"/> the <hi>Keys</hi> were given; therefore that and yours is not the ſame; and that and not yours is underſtood in that Text.</p>
               <p>I ſaid further; If the Keys were committed to the Church, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>6</label> the particular Congregation, you muſt mean it either <hi>objectivè</hi> for the uſe of the Church (but that's not to the purpoſe) or <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectivé,</hi> and then you fall into the extreme of Browniſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To this you anſwer, <q>[I meant it indeed <hi>ſubjectivè,</hi> though not excluding <hi>objectivè:</hi> The particular Church receiveth the power of the Keys, both <hi>ſubjectivè</hi> to it ſelf, and <hi>objectivè,</hi> for it ſelf:]</q> But I reply, and ask, what you mean by <hi>Subjectivè,</hi> to it ſelf? and of what Church you intend it, whether <hi>Entitive,</hi> (as you ſpeak) conſiſting only of beleevers without Officers, or <hi>politicall</hi> with Officers? If you mean that the Church Entitive of beleevers without Officers is the ſubject of the Keys, then they have not only virtually but alſo formally received the Keys, and may adminiſter all Ordinances without Officers (which yet you deny) for <hi>Peter</hi> here received them all formally, and you ſay, as a beleever; then (ſay I) beleevers not only in a <hi>Church</hi> jointly, but even ſingly have received all the power of the Keys formal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and may adminiſter them without any Officers, which is worſe then Browniſm. But I have diſtingu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhed above, when the Church is ſaid to receive the Keys <hi>ſubjectivè</hi> it may be meant, either <hi>immediately</hi> her ſelf, without Officers; or <hi>medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly</hi> by and in her Officers; and I illuſtrated it by the body na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall; As ſight is immediatly truſted with the eye, as the next ſubject of it; but mediatly with the body. In the firſt ſenſe, you cannot ſay, the Church is the immediate ſubject of the Keys<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for then ſhe might immediatly adminiſter them all without Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers (as I ſaid) In the latter ſenſe, it is nothing to your pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, for then, as fight is entruſted with the eye, firſt for the good of the body, ſo the Keys are entruſted with the Officers for the good of the Church:<note place="margin">Par 2. pag. 22.</note> The body is not firſt entruſted with ſight to convey it to the eye, nor are the Keys committed firſt to the Church, to convey them to the Officers. You ſay af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards <q>[If Chriſt have given them (Paſtors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) to the Church, the Church is the Recipient ſubject of them. As if the eye be given to the body, the body is the recipient ſubject of it.]</q> All this is true, in a ſenſe, The Officers are given to the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40476:13"/> Church as the immediate recipient ſubject of them: But is our Queſtion of the Officers, or of the Keys? We ſay, the <hi>Keys</hi> are given to the Church both <hi>objectivè</hi> for its good, with reference to the brethren; and <hi>ſubjectivè</hi> with reference to the Officers: yea, <hi>ſubjectivè</hi> to the Church as the <hi>ſubject</hi> of the Officers, that is, mediatly; but not <hi>ſubjectivè</hi> as the <hi>immediate ſubject</hi> of the Keys: Your compariſon was ill laid; you ſhould have inſtanced in the <hi>ſight</hi> (that reſembles the Keys) not in the <hi>Eye</hi> it ſelf: The body is the <hi>immediate</hi> ſubject of the eye: but the eye, of the ſight. So the Church is the <hi>immediate</hi> ſubject of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but the <hi>Pastors</hi> are the immediate ſubject of the Keys. And this (as I have often ſaid) is evident in the Text in hand; For Chriſt doth not ſay <q>[I give to the Church the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Keys, or the Keys of the Kingdom of heaven that is, of it ſelf) but I give to thee <hi>Peter</hi> the Keys of the kingdom of heaven, that is, of the Church:]</q> not the leaſt colour here, of giving the Keys to the Church.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> pag. 23. Materials of a Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> pag. 27. See pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0, When the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> But I deſire you will conſider your inconſtancy, and the inconſiſtency of your aſſertions. You ſay preſently after the laſt words cited, <q>[Paſtors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Church as integrall parts of the Church, as the Church is <hi>Totum Integrale,</hi>]</q> Then ſay I, they are not given to the Church as meer adjuncts, nor doth the <hi>Church</hi> receive them, as the ſubject of them. And that upon your own reaſon <q>[For integrall parts are intrinſecall and eſſentiall to a <hi>Totum Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grale,</hi> and not extrinſecall, as the object is to a thing.]</q> Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grall parts are not <hi>ſubjects</hi> and <hi>adjuncts</hi> one to another.</p>
               <p>But you ſay <q>[When I wrote that propoſition (in the firſt words of the Way) it was not then in my minde to underſtand any other, but a Congregation of beleevers with Officers; For I ſpake of ſuch a Church whereof <hi>Peter</hi> was one, and he was an Officer.]</q> 1. Whatever was in your minde, I know not, but the words hold out rather a <hi>Congregation</hi> of believers with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Officers (and ſo that acute and judicious M. <hi>Ruth.</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood you,<note place="margin">The Way. p. 1.</note> as well as I) For you ſay there, <q>[The Church to which Chriſt hath committed the Keys of the Kingdom, the power of binding and looſing, the Tables and Seals of his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and (mark that) the Officers and Cenſures of the Church, is a communion of Saints, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> But can the Officers be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40476:13"/> to the Church with Officers? And do not you commonly diſtinguiſh Saints or beleevers from Officers? When you ſaid, <hi>Paſtors</hi> are given to the Church, and the Church is the recipient <hi>ſubject</hi> of them, muſt not the <hi>Church</hi> be taken then for a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Saints without Officers? 2. In your preſent <hi>defence,</hi> you underſtand it all along of a <hi>Church</hi> without Officers, or I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand you not. 3. When you adde <q>[That you ſpake of ſuch a Church whereof <hi>Peter</hi> was one and he was an Officer,] You vary the ſenſe and words of the propoſition.</q> For there you ſay, <q>[The Church to which Chriſt committed the power, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was a company of ſuch (as whereof <hi>Peter</hi> was one) beleevers pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing that faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> Mark that, <hi>one beleever,</hi> not one Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer; And elſewhere you ſay, the were <hi>Keys</hi> committed to <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> not as an Apoſtle or Elder, that is, not as an Officer but as a beleever. How theſe things agree, I ſee not: Yet you will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it (granting that ſenſe) <q>[They have received ſome part of the Keys formally, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> Of which we have ſpoken before, and refer you thither. Only I ſhall obſerve your ſimilitude for illuſtration of your aſſertion: <q>[The ſtock of the vine (grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the root) hath not immediate power to bring forth grapes, yet hath power to produce branches which do bring forth grapes: So the body of the Church of beleevers, though they have not immediate power of rule, authoritatively to diſpenſe the Word, or to adminiſter Sacraments at all, yet they have a power to produce ſuch Officers as may perform the ſame.]</q> But I fear your <hi>ſimilitudes</hi> do deceive you. Do the <hi>Brethren</hi> immediatly give that power to the Officers, which they have not formally in themſelves?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> to Keys, pag. 3.</note> Did not the Officers receive their power immediatly from Chriſt or his Apoſtles, who had that power formally in themſelves? Have not your <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facers</hi> to the Keys, told us, that your ſelf lay this fundamentall Maxime, <q>[That look whatever power or right any of the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſours and ſubjects thereof may have, they have it each alike immediatly (in reſpect of a mediation of delegation or depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on each other) from Chriſt, and ſo are each the firſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of that power which is allotted to them?]</q> But now you make the Officers to depend immediatly upon the Church of beleevers; and to derive their power from them by mediation
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40476:14"/> or delegation, as the branches derive their being and vertue to produce grapes, from the ſtock of the Vine. Which if it be not to jump with the <hi>Browniſts,</hi> who place all power radically and originally in the Church of beleevers, and make the Officers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive it as their ſervants immediatfy from them; I muſt profeſſe I underſtand nothing in this controverſie:<note place="margin">Survey part. 1. p. 195. prop. 4.</note> Doth not M. <hi>Hooker</hi> make the <hi>Church</hi> of beleevers the firſt ſubject of all <hi>Church</hi> power? and do not the Browniſts juſt ſo? whereas you (ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times at leaſt in the judgement of your brethren here, as afore) make two firſt ſubjects of the power of the Keyes and each to have it immediatly from Chriſt: I deſire you would conſider whom M. <hi>Hooker</hi> meant in thoſe words <q>[That conceit is more wide from the mark, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ]</q> pag 195. ſect. 2. It is ſtrange that all this while you ſhould agree no better.</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>7</label> I ſaid laſtly, The Church there meant is called the <hi>Kingdom of heaven,</hi> but a particular <hi>Congregation</hi> of beleevers is never cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſo: being but a member of it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> You anſwer, <q>[It is not materiall, whether it be called ſo or no, it is enough it is called a Church, yea, as diſtinguiſhed from <hi>Church-Officers, Acts</hi> 25.22,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Suprà,</hi> pag. 7.</note> 23. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> I gave the ſenſe and roſolution of that Text afore; The ſum is this, it doth not hold a <hi>Church</hi> of beleevers, as exiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without Officers; for that Church had Officers: but only diſtinguiſheth the <hi>Integrall</hi> parts (as your ſelf call them above) of that Church into Officers and members;] <q>[The Apoſtles, Elders, and whole Church; <hi>ver.</hi> 22.]</q> that is, the brethren or beleevers, <hi>ver.</hi> 23. <hi>aſſembled together,</hi> ver. 25. which is no more then if he had ſaid, the <hi>whole Church,</hi> conſiſting of Apoſtles, El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and Brethren. But you muſt remember that you are diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the power of the <hi>Keyes</hi> to be given to a <hi>Church</hi> belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers without Officers and you bring an inſtance of a <hi>Church</hi> that had Officers: Shew (if you can) a <hi>Church</hi> of beleevers, exiſting without Officers, which took upon them the name of a Church, or the tide of the <hi>Kingdom of heaven.</hi> I yet beleeve, whereever the <hi>Church</hi> is called the <hi>Kingdom of heaven,</hi> in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, it is meant of the whole Church, not of any particular Congregation. Your own Texts produced do hold out as much, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.1. It is called a vineyard, which ſignifies either the ſtate of the Goſpel, or the whole viſible Church; If he had
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40476:14"/> meant it of particular Churches, he would have rather ſaid, into his vineyards; for all thoſe Officers could not be hired for one particular <hi>Church:</hi> You ſay, ["It was into this or that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church reſpectively] true, with reſpect to the whole vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible <hi>Church,</hi> which is but one. A man that hath a large vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, hires ſervants to work, in ſeveral places or parts of that vineyard; but this or that part is not called a vineyard, but with reſpect to the whole, they are all hired to labour in his vineyard. Or what if that Parable be rather underſtood of particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, then particular Congregations? God cals all Chriſtians into his <hi>Church,</hi> and ſets them to work; Some come in at one hour, ſome at another; they that come firſt, think they deſerve more, then they that come in late, at the eleventh hour: Chriſt would intimate, that God is free, and his grace free to do what he will with his own; and there is no merit at all; Many are called but few are choſen: But your Expoſition reſtrains the parable only to Officers, as diſtinct from the Church of belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers. The like my be ſaid of your ſecond Text, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.1, 2. It is not meant as an a deſcription of the eſtate of each particular Church, as you ſtrain, rather then interpret it: but of every particular profeſſing Chriſtian, whereof ſome have <hi>lamps</hi> of profeſſion, but no oyl of true grace; others have both: And the ſcope of the parable is intimated in the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or application, <hi>ver.</hi> 23. <q>[Watch ye therefore <hi>(every one of you)</hi> for you know not the day nor hour when the Son of man cometh,]</q> Your next of <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.21. is wider from the mark, <hi>[The Kingdom of God "is within you,]</hi> that is, either the Meſſias whom you ſeek as abſent, is now among you, as <hi>Beza,</hi> or the power of the Goſpel is within you or upon you. Thoſe other of <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.6. and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. are as much miſtaken, if applied to a particular Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. All the faithfull are Kings and Prieſts, and all together, are a <hi>Kingdom of Prieſts,</hi> both Officers and beleevers. I ſuppoſe you will not apply this either only to the <hi>Officers,</hi> or only to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers, but to both ſingly and jointly, and reſpectively to the <hi>whole Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To conclude this whole firſt Section, I added, a particular <hi>Congregation</hi> is but a member or Corporation of that kingdom: and it were as improper to call a <hi>Congregation</hi> Chriſts kingdom,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40476:15"/> as to call <hi>London</hi> the kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> You anſwer, <q>[E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſimilar part of a ſimilar body doth properly partake both in the name and nature of the whole; Every part of water is water, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſuch a part of ſuch a body is a particular viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church.But ſuch is not the ſtate of <hi>London,</hi> &amp;c.</q> ] You ſaid a little above <q>[It was not in your minde to underſtand any other particular <hi>Congregation,</hi> but one furniſhed with Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers:]</q> But then if you will ſpeak properly and ſtrictly, you cannot ſay, that a particular Congregation of Officers and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers is a ſimilar part of a ſimilar body; for it is a d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſimilar body conſiſting of diſſimilar parts: and ſo <hi>London,</hi> and it, agree in ſtate; and that Church can no more properly be called the Kingdom of heaven, then <hi>London</hi> the kingdom of <hi>England.</hi> Again, if you will (to help your ſelf out of this Labyrinth) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it of a particuar <hi>Church</hi> without Officers, you fall into another gulf as bad as the former. For if particular Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions conſiſting of ſimilar parts (of beleevers only) may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Kingdoms, as they are called <hi>Churches,</hi> then it will fairly follow, that every particular member of that ſimilar body, may be called not only a Church, but a Kingdom too; becauſe <hi>every ſimilar part of a ſimilar body</hi> (it is your own reaſon) <hi>doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly partake in the Name and Nature of the whole:</hi> So then, as every drop of water is water, ſo every member of ſuch a Church, is a Church; and of ſuch a Kingdom, is a Kingdom. Your fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of metaphors and Parables too far, is guilty of theſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages; as I elſewhere often ſhew; where I alſo ſhew how a particular Church conſiſting of Officers and beleevers, may, in a candid ſenſe be ſaid to be a ſimilar body, to which I referre you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. II.</hi> What the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven are.</head>
               <p>IF in opening what the <hi>Keys</hi> of the kingdom of heaven be, it was not your intent to enumerate them all diſtinctly and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, (as you here ſay) Surely you intended not the buſineſſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40476:15"/> you had in hand, when you were purpoſely engaged to anſwer this Queſtion. What are the <hi>Keyes</hi> of this Kingdom? would not any Reader expect (from an Expoſitor, of that text) a full and perfect <hi>enumeration</hi> of the Keys? what, and how many they are? Had you ſaid only thus <q>[The Keys are the Ordinances which Chriſt hath inſtituted to be adminiſtred in his Church.]</q> You might afterwards have referred them (as you ſay) to their ſeverall ſubjects. But when you adde <q>[As the preaching of the Word, as alſo the adminiſtration of the Seals and Cenſures;]</q> Would not any Reader take it for a full diſtribution of the Keys? And when you adde <q>[By the opening and applying of theſe both the gates of the <hi>Church</hi> here, and of heaven hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter are opened or ſhut to the ſons of men.]</q> Would not any man think, theſe were all the <hi>Keys</hi> neceſſary, and alſufficient for thoſe ends on earth and in heaven?</p>
               <p>But (ſay you) <q>[In inſtancing theſe, I ſuppoſed no man would be of ſo narrow apprehenſion, as not to conceive thoſe things to be included, without which theſe cannot duely be perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. As vocation unto ſuch adminiſtrations, and ſome who have power from Chriſt to give ſuch a vocation.]</q> But I pray Sir, are theſe any part of the <hi>Keys</hi> themſelves? If a Steward be truſted with the Keys of the Family (as <hi>Peter</hi> with the Keys of the Church:) there muſt be doors and locks, and ſervants to be let in, or ſhut out; but are thoſe any part of the Keys? Mend your diſtribution of the Keys; and will you ſay, The Keyes are <hi>vocation,</hi> and ſome that have power to give ſuch a vocation? We (ſuch is the narrowneſſe of our apprehenſion) think your diſtribution afore-given, is full enough; nor can we tell (pardon our dulneſſe) how you can mend it, but you will make it worſe. We have been accuſtomed ſo long to that ancient diſtribution of <hi>Clavis Scientiae</hi> (which you call preaching of the Word) and <hi>Clavis poteſtatis</hi> (which you call <hi>Administration of Seals and Cenſures</hi>) that we wonder at your new pick-locks, preſented to the world, as Keys of the <hi>kingdom of heaven.</hi> And I yet think, your new <hi>diſtribution</hi> labour under ſo many <hi>Incongruities</hi> (as <hi>Vind. Clav.</hi> hath given you to underſtand, though you are not pleaſed to take notice of them, or to vindicate them,] that it is far worſe then the old one, ſo long received in the Churches of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40476:16"/> Chriſt. I had thought to have added your own words (appliable enough to your new diſtribution) in end of <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 6. of the <hi>Keys,</hi> but I forbear.</p>
               <p>It ſeems to me (though you inſinuate the contrary) to be of great weight for the expediting of many controverſies about the Keys, and your <hi>new Way,</hi> to know what thoſe Keys be, and what Ordinances they include. Is not one main controverſie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt you and us, about the nature and extent of the Keys, and who are the Key-bearers? which cannot be decided, unleſſe we know what be thoſe Keys. But let us hear your new defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Keys: <q>Keys of the kingdom of heaven are ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all powers, to diſpenſe the Treaſures of his Kingdom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> Is not this almoſt the ſame with that afore, <hi>Keys</hi> are the <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances</hi> of Chriſt to be adminiſtred in his Church, for opening and ſhutting the gates of the Church here, and of heaven hereafter? But what mean you by <hi>spirituall powers?</hi> you mean <q>[Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall callings and ſpirituall gifts fitting for them, enabling to ſome ſpirituall Acts, for theſe are Ordinances.]</q> I pray Sir, is every ſpirituall calling, and every ſpirituall gift fitting for them, a Key intended in the text to be given to <hi>Peter?</hi> callings and gifts help to diſpenſe the Keys, but they are no <hi>Keys:</hi> But they are Ordinances? Be it ſo, is every Ordinance a <hi>Key?</hi> The Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons office is an Ordinance (and the Widows too, ſay you) and <hi>ſpirituall gifts</hi> are requiſite to fit for that calling; but is a <hi>Deacon</hi> or his <hi>office</hi> a <hi>Key?</hi> and a <hi>Key</hi> given to <hi>Peter</hi> in that Text? Prayer and ſinging are Ordinances, but who ever num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred them among the <hi>Keys?</hi> Well, what are the <hi>Treaſures</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed by thoſe powers or <hi>Keys?</hi> 
                  <q>[I mean by them (ſay you) the Word, Seals, and cenſures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> Before you ſaid the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the word, and Adminiſtration of the Seals and Cenſures, were theſe <hi>Keys:</hi> and now you call them the <hi>Treaſurers</hi> to be diſpenſed by the <hi>Keys:</hi> What incongruity is here? Now let us hear your <hi>Distribution</hi> of the <hi>Keys,</hi> according to this your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition: <q>[<hi>Keys,</hi> ſpirituall powers, are either the Key of Knowledge or Faith (both one w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th you) or the Key of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: The Key of Order is either the Key of power, or the Key of Authority or Rule:]</q> Is not this an accurate diſtribution? The <hi>spirituall powers</hi> are either <hi>Keys</hi> of power or of Authority?
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40476:16"/> And is not the <hi>Key</hi> of knowledge a key of order, an Ordinance peculiar to ſome order or office of men? what confuſion is here? In a word, your new definition of the <hi>Keys</hi> better fits the <hi>Key-bearers</hi> then the <hi>Keys</hi> themſelves, <hi>ver.</hi> 9. A Paſtor or Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher is a ſpirituall power given by Chriſt to his <hi>Church,</hi> to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe the Treaſures of his kingdom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And your own Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition fits it better: By ſpirituall powers is meant, <hi>ſpirituall cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings:</hi> ſuch is the calling of a Paſtor: and ſpiritual gifts are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite for the fitting of them to ſpiritual Acts: But no man ever ſaid, that a <hi>Paſtor</hi> was a <hi>Key,</hi> but a Steward to diſpenſe the Keys. New waies muſt coin new notions and diſtinctions, to make them as amiable, as ſtrange. But the <hi>old way</hi> is the good way.</p>
               <p n="1">1. And now you come to animadvert upon my animadverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; 1 I ſaid you confuted your ſcope in the whole book, which is to give the people a ſhare in the government of the Church: This you peremptorily deny to be your ſcope, and ſay I miſtake your meaning. Let your <hi>Praefacers</hi> ſpeak firſt,<note place="margin">Praef. to Keys, pag. 3.</note> 
                  <q>[His ſcope is to demonſtrate a diſtinct and ſeveral ſtate, and intereſt of power, in matters of common concernment, vouchſafed to each of theſe (the Officers and people) and diſperſed among both, by charter from the Lord: as in ſome corporate Towns, the Aldermen as Rulers, and a Common Counſell a body of the people.]</q> which that it amounts to a ſhare in the Ruling pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, is demonſtrated in my <hi>Vind. Clav.</hi> in anſwer to that preface, and in the Tract it ſelf; But you take no notice of it. Next, let your own books ſpeak; wherein you often give the brethren without Officers power to ordain Officers, and to cenſure them all without Officers; which if they be not the <hi>higheſt acts of Rule,</hi> and ſo the brethren have the greateſt ſhare in the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I ſhall ſtill profeſſe my <hi>Ignorance</hi> in this controverſie. And upon my obſervation, you deny them power in nothing, but adminiſtration of Sacraments: You allow them power in juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, by giving them power in <hi>admiſſion</hi> and <hi>ejection</hi> of mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and Officers: You allow them liberty in preaching the Word, only not ordinarily, nor ſo authoritatively as to Paſtor or Teacher: what can you give them more but adminiſtration of Sacraments; and that being leſſe an Act of Rule, then the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, you may go on, and grant them that too, or they will take it, and ſo they do.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:40476:17"/>
               <p>I ſaid, in proſecution of my charge, of your confuting the ſcope of your book, If the Keys be the Ordinances of Chriſt, (there by you ſpecified) preaching and adminiſtration of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Cenſures, they are given for the Church of beleevers, <hi>objectivè,</hi> but are never in Scripture, or all antiquity ſaid to be given to the Church <hi>ſubjectivè:</hi> You are pleaſed to <hi>deride</hi> me, as if I had not read all Antiquity, which I profeſſe I have not (though in this particular controverſie it is eaſie to finde what Antiquity hath ſaid) or had forgotten what is recorded by the moſt ancient Antiquity, for the ſpace of the firſt three hundred years: But of that you vouchſafe not to give me any account, how pertinent ſoever to our preſent buſineſſe, but referre me to that account you have given M. <hi>Baily;</hi> to whom (in way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitall, not of revenge) I ſhall referre you to wait for your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
               <p>But you ſay <q>[what power you give to the Church of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers <hi>ſubjectivè,</hi> you alledge Scriptures for it, which when <hi>Vindex</hi> taketh in hand to evade them, you ſhall return him an anſwer.]</q> You did alledge Scripture, and the Aſſertor (not Avenger) did in their place anſwer them (not evaded them, as you phraſe it) and expected your reply; but I perceive he may go ſeek it, for you never come at the place, where it is hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; though you promiſe here, and once or twice more, you would do it; but either evaded it, or forgot it, of which more anon.</p>
               <p>It ſounds very ill (I ſaid) at firſt hearing to ſay, that the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren have any power in the Keys, or Ordinances of preaching, or adminiſtring Seals or Cenſures: you anſwer, (<q>If thoſe, preaching the Word, and adminiſtring Seals, were all the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and no more, I ſay true, it would ſound ill at firſt, at ſecond, and third hearing too, to ſay, The people have any power to exerciſe theſe Ordinances,</q> ] <hi>&amp;c.</hi>But 1. Why do you leave out <hi>Cenſures,</hi> which not only I put in, but your ſelf alſo, in defining the Keys? Does it not ſound ill, at firſt ſecond, and third hearing, to all reformed Churches (but your own and ſuch like) that the people have any power, yea, the <hi>greateſt pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> to exerciſe cenſures? For they can cenſure all their Officers, but all their Officers without them cannot cenſure them, nor
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40476:17"/> any one of them: It is indeed no unpleaſant ſound to you, or your people: yea, it would ſound very ill and harſh to you, at leaſt to your people, to hear, That they have no power in the Keys mentioned, preaching and adminiſtring of Seals and Cenſures. But if thoſe Keys were given to <hi>Peter,</hi> they were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to him, either as an <hi>Elder,</hi> and then the people have nothing to do with them at all, one or other: Or as a Beleever, but then they may as well exerciſe the Ordinances of preaching and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtring Seals, as exerciſe and adminiſter the Ordinance of Cenſures.</p>
               <p>But you go on, by way of <hi>Recrimination</hi> (I ſay not by way of <hi>Revenge</hi>) with an argument, <hi>ad hominem</hi> 
                  <q>[You marvell it ſhould ſound ſo ill (to allow the people a power in cenſures) to them whoſe ears have been wonted long, to hear of ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſions and Excommunications, by Chancellors and Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, who generally are no Miniſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> Truly Sir, this toucheth not me, who have as well thought it to ſound ill, at firſt or ſecond hearing, that Chancellors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> no Miniſters, ſhould ſuſpend and excommunicate, as I now think it harſh to hear, this power is allowed to, and practiſed by the people. Though people may perhaps be the better men, yet not ſo well authorized, as ſome Chancellors and Commiſſaries (for ſome of them were Miniſters) who had more colour of Authority to ſuſpend, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then your people have, who are quite out of office. But you wonder more that I that could alledge all Antiquity, ſhould think it to ſound ill <q>[Who know what reverend Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, ancient <hi>Tertullian</hi> giveth of the Brethrens power, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and what <hi>Cyprian</hi> gives to the people, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> I had thought to let you wait for your anſwer, from M. <hi>Baily;</hi> but ſeeing you are pleaſed to vouchſafe me the Teſtimonies, I ſhall anticipate his anſwer in the mean time. 1. For <hi>Tertullians,</hi> I finde you cite him not at all to M. <hi>Baily,</hi> as if then you took it to be of no great ſtrength. What ſaith <hi>Tertullian? Quum probi, cum boni coeunt,</hi> &amp;c. <q>[When honeſt, good, godly, chaſte people, meet together, it is not to be called a faction, but a Court.]</q> What is this to power of the people in cenſures? Unleſſe you begge it hence, that the word <hi>Curia</hi> ſignifies a Court? But I pray, what mention is here of Officers at all? Did the people at that time
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40476:18"/> cenſure alone without their Officers? You will hardly prove that: or are not Officers good and honeſt men? Or doe good men never meet but in a Court to cenſure? As for <hi>Cyprian</hi> you leave me in the dark, to go look what he ſayes; or to turn back to what you ſay to M. <hi>Baily:</hi> I ſhall conſider the place, and his Teſtimonies. In the firſt, you clearly to my underſtanding confute your own way of Ordination of Miniſters: Thus <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> ſpeaks <q>[As they have received from the Apoſtles, ſo they hold it, that for the orderly celebration of Ordination, all the neighbour Biſhops of the ſame Province, where a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter is to be ordained, come together to that people, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Of <hi>Sabinus</hi> he ſaies, this Office was put upon him by the ſuffrage of the whole brotherhood, and by the judgement of all the Paſtors preſent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo hands were impoſed on him.]</q> I pray, do you gather all the <hi>neighbour Biſhops</hi> or Paſtors of the Province, where a Miniſter is to be ordained? Do thoſe Paſtors impoſe hands upon him? yet theſe, <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaies, they received from the Apoſtles. True it is, the Miniſter was choſen in the preſence of the people, and good reaſon, as to whom his life is beſt known: But the judgement of his abilities was in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors; as alſo the Impoſition of hands. But the people had their Suffrage; that is nothing, but ſome rationall conſent, or ſome manifeſtation of their approbation, not any authoritative vote, or ordination.<note place="margin">See the Way. pa. 41. and 58.</note> But this is not the new way of Ordination; for you allow the brotherhood, ſuffrage, conſent, judgement and impoſition of hands too, upon their Officers. This you never received from the Apoſtles. Another Teſtimony is this: <q>[The people fearing God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have chiefly the power of chooſing worthy Miniſters, and refuſing the unworthy.]</q> But power of election of one Miniſter, rather then another, and rejection of an unworthy Miniſter, is not denied the people of God: That Election is but their conſent or approbation of ſuch a Miniſter, as the Paſtors in their judgement, think fit and worthy: and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection is but withdrawing communion from one unworthy, and judged fit to be excommunicated. But this we ſay is no part of the power of the keys, we doubt not but pious and godly wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhould have this liberty or priviledge to except againſt known unworthy perſons, and to withdraw communion from
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40476:18"/> them; yet ſurely, you will not allow them power in the Keys. When <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaies <q>[All things ſhall be examined, you being preſent and judging,] He means not a judgement of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, but of diſcretion.</q> And the laſt place, <q>[I determined to do nothing without your counſell and conſent,]</q> declares his meaning fully to be for conſent, not Authority: And ſo thoſe times give no expreſſe lineaments of Congregationall diſcipline. Shew us in any Antiquity of Scripture or ſtory, that the people had power without Officers to create or ordain Officers, to impoſe hands upon them, or to cenſure all their Officers; or you ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the preſent controverſie.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When you had ſaid <q>[The Keys convey not Soveraign power, but ſtewardly,]</q> I inferred, that this clearly excludeth the people, for they have no ſtewardly or miniſteriall power over themſelves (I might have added, much leſſe over their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers,) You anſwer by a queſtion, ["As if the people were not Stewards of the grace of God given to them? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] But truly Sir, this is no better then a fine eluſion. To take <hi>Stewards</hi> in a larger ſenſe then I intended it. <hi>Stewards</hi> to me are Officers, and can the people be <hi>Stewards</hi> over their Stewards? Your ſelf ſay, <hi>pag.</hi> 28. <q>[It implieth a contradiction, that the Church ſhould be its own Officer, for the very term of Officer im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plieth ſubordination.]</q> So ſay I, it implieth a contradiction, that the Church ſhould be its own Steward; And again, <hi>p.</hi> 30. <q>[We acknowledge (ſay you) that a company of profeſſing believers, deſtitute of Officers, are not Stewards by office, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> Then (ſay I) you anſwer equivocally; taking the word in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſenſe, then it is commonly taken in this controverſie <q>[Let a man esteem of us as Stewards of the myſteries of God, <hi>1 Cor. 4.1.</hi>]</q> Did not the Apoſtle there mean it only of Officers? Nor will the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> help you out:<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.10.</note> For either he takes <hi>Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> in the ſtrict ſenſe for Officers, with reference to the 11. <hi>verſe.</hi> Or in the large ſenſe, for any <hi>Dispenſers</hi> of any kinde of gifts, as the referring it to the 9. <hi>verſe</hi> ſeems to carry it. Now we take the word in one ſenſe, and you in another, and ſo you anſwer nothing, but miſleade your Reader, while you e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade.</p>
               <p>Yet you go on; ["If they have received any gift of grace,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40476:19"/> they are either Stewards of it, or Lords.] Apply this to <hi>women,</hi> yea, to Infidels; If they have received any gift or grace they are either Stewards of it, or Lords: Lords they are not; what are they elſe, Stewards? they are your own words. But we an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, it is not any gift that we are ſpeaking of, but the gift of the Keys; that's your firſt evaſion: And then we ſay, they are neither Stewards nor Lords, in our ſenſe of Stewards, but mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the family, in ſubordination to the Lords and Stewards; having nothing to do with the Keys at all. But, ſay you, <q>[E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of Officers is a publike gift, and that muſt be diſpenſed publikely,]</q> Grant <hi>Election</hi> of Officers to be a publike gift, and yeeld it to the people, yet (ſay we) it is no part of the gift of the Keys. Laſtly, when you ſay <q>[the people are not as Lords, to elect whom they liſt, but as Stewards and Miniſters to Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> either you make them Officers, or you doe prevaricate all along his Paragraph, and that I think you doe.</p>
               <p>And the like you do in the word <hi>(calling)</hi> which I ſaid ſhould be taken of ſome <hi>speciall calling</hi> or Office, which would exclude the people from having an office in the Church, or any power of the Keys. You ſay, <q>[There is no reaſon for that, if ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall denote a ſpecification of a calling, diſtinct from other members of the Church: but if it only ſignifie a diſtinct ſtate or order, from ſuch as are not members; ſo it is true, every member hath a ſpeciall calling from ſuch as are not yet recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as members of a particular Church.]</q> But, Sir, you cannot well underſtand it otherwiſe then I do, when you ſpeak of a ſpeciall calling, in ſuch, as to whom the <hi>Keyes</hi> are given, with a power to open and ſhut the gates of heaven, that is, the Church. For I ſuppoſe every member of the Church particular hath not ſuch a ſpeciall calling, or ſuch power of the Keys, to open and ſhut the gates of heaven: as women and children for example: yet have they in your ſenſe a ſpeciall calling, ſtate, or order in the Church; as was more fully ſaid in <hi>Vind. Clav.</hi> And ſurely in this controverſie <hi>ſpeciall calling,</hi> and office, have ever been taken for the ſame thing, not for ſtate, or place, or order, at large. Beleevers not yet members of a particular Church, have a diſtinct calling, in your ſenſe, from Infidels, a ſtate,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40476:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> place, order, in the viſible Catholike Church: yea, if they be men, they have as good a ſtate, order, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in a particular Church, as your women and children have, in regard of any power of the <hi>Keys.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet you ſay, <q>[Every member of a particular Church hath a calling to put forth ſome acts of power of his own Church, which members of another Church have not there:]</q> Had you not ſaid <hi>(His)</hi> I would have asked what acts of power women may put forth in their particular Church; yet certainly women may put forth ſome acts of power in their own Church; or elſe their calling, ſtate, place, order, is very mean and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptible. There is no member of the body naturall, not the leaſt, but it hath in your notion, a function, action, office, in the body, a power to put forth ſome acts in its own body, which it cannot do in another body, nor the members of another body in its bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. The queſtion is not of ſome acts of power, but ſome acts of power of the Keys; which is an office power. But ſay you ſtill, <q>[Every member of the body of a particular Church (women and all ſay I) hath ſome function and action, or (as the new Tranſlation) Office in the body: <hi>Ro.</hi> 12.4, 5. All the members have not the ſame office; which implieth, they all of them have ſome office, though not the ſame.]</q> Truly Sir, this is but a prevarication: Fos 1. By <hi>body</hi> there, is not meant a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Church, but the whole Church: <q>[We, being many, are one body in Chriſt, and every one members one of another,]</q> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> puts in himſelf, and he was no member of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in your ſenſe, 2. When they render the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi> they either mean it largely, and not for a <hi>speciall office,</hi> as we take it, or ſtrictly, and then it relates to the Officers of the Church only, as the following verſes may ſeem to inſinuate, ["whether Prophecy or Miniſtry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] where your ſelf and others, do finde all the Officers of the Church: and ſo taken, it is nothing to your purpoſe, but rather againſt you.</p>
               <p>When I ſaid, you added that explication <q>[whether it be their office, or place, and order in the Church,]</q> to ſteal in the intereſt of the people, in ſome ſhare of the Keys: you an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <q>[It is not ſtealth but juſtice to give to every man his own: the Pſalmiſt foretold it in a new ſong, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 159.9. Such
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40476:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> honour have all his Saints, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> But you muſt firſt prove it their own, and that that Text is ſo to be underſtood; or elſe it is as well ſacrilege or ſtealth (taking it from the right owners) if the Lord hath not given them this honour: as it is to deny it, or take it from them, if the Lord hath given it to them.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, (and ſo you will have done with me) you conclude, <q>[It is not every place or order in the Church, that giveth pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to receive the Ordinances, much leſſe, power themſelves to to diſpenſe Ordinances: as children and women, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> This is very true: yet you aſſerted before: <q>[Every member of a particular Church hath a calling to put forth ſome Acts of power, in his own Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> Then ſay I, women and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, for they are members too: yea, we think, except but that of ſpeaking in the Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.34. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.11, 12. expre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly forbidden, and we do not finde any one thing granted by Chriſt (in reſpect of the power of the Keys) to men, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon members of the Church, that women may not be allowed to act; as I often told you, in <hi>Vind. Clav.</hi> 1. Women (widows at leaſt, who contribute maintenance) may have ſome power in chooſing (that is in your ſenſe) ordaining Officers. 2. To pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound juſt exceptions againſt ſuch as offer themſelves to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. 3. To admoniſh in caſe of private ſcandall. 4. To judge with a judgement of diſcretion; you ſometimes allow the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren no more, <hi>Keyes,</hi> pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4. They may tell the Church, they may conſent and concurre with the Elders at leaſt paſſively. 5. To withdraw from one excommunicate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as was ſuggeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to you elſewhere. And now before I conclude, I ſhall ſet before you an obſervation of your <hi>inconstancy,</hi> in aſſigning the firſt ſubject of the power of the Keys; The Keys were given, 1. To <hi>Peter,</hi> as an Apoſtle, as an Elder, and as a beleever. 2. To <hi>Peter,</hi> not as an Apoſtle, not as an Elder, but as a believer; and conſequently to all believers. 3. Not to believers as believers, but as making publike confeſſion of their faith, before the Lord and their brethren: <hi>The way cleared,</hi> part, 2. pag. 39. and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like profeſſion of their obedience of the faith, to the Lord Jeſus, in the publike Ordinances of his worſhip, <hi>pag.</hi> 40. 4. Not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers as believers, but as believers covenanting, and fitly capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble according to Chriſts appointment; M. <hi>Hooker</hi> Surv. <hi>par.</hi> 1.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:40476:20"/> 
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 203. Or as you here; it is not every place, or order in the Church that giveth power to receive or diſpenſe Ordinances; as not that place or order of children and women, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whereas when firſt you began, you aſſerted, <hi>The Keys were given to Peter as a beleever,</hi> and ſo by your own argument, <hi>a quatenus tale,</hi> to all beleevers, as beleevers; you are forced to make ſeverall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions, to help it out; That poſition that needs ſo many di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions, gives ſtrong ſuſpition it is not the truth. And now I ſhall conclude this ſecond Section with your own words, <q>[Let every ſoul enjoy ſuch priviledges and liberties, as the Lord hath given him (or her) in their place and order, and neither effect nor attempt more.]</q> Happy had it been for the Church of God, if this had been done.<note place="margin">The Keys p. 6.</note> I ſhall but minde you of what I ſuggeſted to you in <hi>Vind. Clav.</hi> pag. 13. in your own words; I pray you ſeriouſly conſider, <q>[Whether by this ſacrilegious breach of order, inveſting the people with a Key of power, even above thoſe Elders that labour in the word and doctrine, to open and ſhut the doors againſt them (<hi>p.</hi> 9. of <hi>Keys</hi>) (which is the breaking of the files and ranks in an Army) Satan is not like again to rout and ruine a great part of the liberty and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Church-Officers, and the purity of the Churches, and of all the Ordinances of Chriſt in them.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. III.</head>
               <p>I now expected, you ſhould have gone on, with <hi>Vind. Clav.</hi> and have vindicated your book and ſelf, from thoſe other many wickedneſſes and contradictions, charged (I ſtill think) juſtly upon you: But you fairly (if you doe not rather in way of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge,) ſhake hands with me, or rather ſlightly ſhake me off, and never meet again. And this is the more remarkable, becauſe you promiſe at leaſt three times (with atteſtation of the name of God twice at leaſt) <hi>pag.</hi> 15. and <hi>pag.</hi> 16. and again, <hi>pag.</hi> 19 a further conſideration of them. In the firſt place thus, <q>[when <hi>Vindex</hi> takes in hand to evade the Scriptures alledged, I ſhall return him (God willing) further anſwer:]</q> In the ſecond place thus again, <q>[What reaſon there is for their (the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns)
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:40476:21"/> power in Church-cenſures, we ſhall further conſider (God willing) in its place.]</q> To which places you never come near; Is not this to take Gods Name in vain? And new in the third Section you promiſe, though you undertake thoſe two Reverend Antagoniſts, M. <hi>B.</hi> and M. <hi>Ruth.</hi> 
                  <q>[Yet by the way, not to neglect what perſonal exceptions <hi>Vindex</hi> hath taken at your ſelf;]</q> But reading over the following diſcourſe, I finde not that you do ſo much as take any notice of me, or your threefold engagement; but as if <hi>Vindex</hi> were ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible perſon, that deſerved to be ſlighted, as his beſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; you neglect all his; I ſhall only ſay,
<q>
                     <l>"Et ſi ego dignus hac contumelia vel maximè,</l>
                     <l>"At tu indignus, qui faceres tamen,</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Who both are charged with ſo many contradictions, which (for your own honour) it concerned you to anſwer; and alſo have charged your ſelf three times to give a further anſwer. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this, there were ſeven Chapters in <hi>Vind. Clav.</hi> wherein you were not a little concerned to give (if not me) the world ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction: and you are pleaſed to anſwer (if you have anſwered) but to one, and but to two Sections of three in that chapter, which is a ſlighting and contempt of an adverſary, not uſually heard of. And now, I leave it to the Judicious Reader to reſolve, who deſerves beſt,<note place="margin">Adverſarius litis, non per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonae.</note> and moſt juſtly, the name and title of <hi>Vindex</hi> or <hi>Avenger.</hi> Yet you give ſome reaſon of this ſlighting and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect: for ſo you ſay, <q>[I conceive it loſſe of time and labour, to argue the queſtion with <hi>Vindex</hi> alone, whoſe exceptions ſo far as they concern the point in controverſie, are but collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons out of the writings of others; who have more diſtinctly and elaborately diſputed the cauſe:]</q> I pray Sir, why do you conceive it loſſe of time and labour to argue this Queſtion with me? Do you mean, your anſwers would be ſo unſatiſfying (as the former now will appear to be) as that the time and labour would be ill ſpent? Your Reader will think ſo, if you anſwer no better to that remaining, then to what is gone before, And why do you ſay this Queſtion? as if there were no more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt us then this, But I moſt of all admire why you ſhould ſay, my exc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ptions are but collections out of the writings of others: I beleeve the Reader will finde my exceptions are Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40476:21"/> of contradictions, out of your own writings, more then out of others. And I can ſincerely profeſſe, I conſulted with none, or very few books of this controverſie, but comparing your books one with another, my own reaſon and judgement ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted to me thoſe contradictions in them, that left me altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unſatisfied in your way, and at this day, I am left ſo ſtill; if not more confirmed; that the Independent way is not the way of God, that is ſo inconſiſtent with the Scriptures, and with it ſelf.</p>
               <p>That others have more elaborately diſputed this cauſe, I ſhall eaſily yeeld; but I think I may truly ſay without vanity, none have more diſtinctly diſcovered the weakneſſes of your proofs, and your contradictions to your ſelves, in holding out your Way, then I have done. Nor am I at all troubled that you chuſe rather to conſider what hath been written by Learned and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend M. <hi>Rutherford</hi> and M. <hi>Baily</hi> (though you ſere M. <hi>Baily</hi> as you doe me, never name him more in all your following diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe) had you but made good your promiſes, to conſider alſo what I had ſaid, to vindicate your ſelf from your contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and to clear the truth in queſtion. But ſeeing you are pleaſed ſo to neglect me, I hope you will not be troubled if I conceive it loſſe of time and labour to follow you any further; and conſider what Learned and Reverend M. <hi>Hooker</hi> hath ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borately written in this controverſie Only give me leave to preſent you with a Scheme of your remaining contradictions, or contrarieties at leaſt noted in <hi>Vind. Clav.</hi> out of your own books: and then leave you to your choiſe, whether you will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile them or confeſſe them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="table">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:40476:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>A Scheme of Contradictions and Contrarieties in the Independent way.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <p n="1">1. THe Keys were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to <hi>Peter</hi> as an Apoſtle, as an Elder, and as a beleever. So the ſenſe moſt fill, The <hi>Keys, pag.</hi> 4.</p>
                           <p>It appears, that Chriſt gave the Keys to the fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity with the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, <hi>Ib.</hi> See alſo <hi>the Way cleared,</hi> par. 2. pag. 22.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1. The power of the Keys is given to <hi>Peter</hi> not as an Apoſtle, nor as as Elder, but as a profeſt believer, <hi>The way</hi> pag. 27.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <p n="1">1. <hi>Peter</hi> received no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> the Keys meerly as a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever, but as a beleeve publikely profeſſing hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> faith, <hi>&amp;c. The Way clea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red,</hi> par. 2. f. 39.</p>
                           <p>Not beleevers as belee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vers, but as beleevers co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>venanting, and fitly capa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble according to Chriſt appointment, M. <hi>Hooker</hi> Surv. par. 1. p. 203.</p>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2. The Keys are given to the <hi>Church</hi> of belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers <hi>The Way,</hi> p. 1. that is a combination of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful men: as M. <hi>Hooker.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>2. The Key of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge belongeth to all, the faithfull, whether joyned to any particular Church or no. <hi>The Keys,</hi> pag. 11.</cell>
                        <cell>2. The Key of Know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge is given not only to the Church, but to ſome before they ente<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> into the Church, <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> Keyes,</hi> p. 11.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3. The Key of order is common to all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church, <hi>Keys</hi> p. 8. Then (ſay we) to women and children.</cell>
                        <cell>3. It is not every place or order in the Church that giveth power to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Ordinances, much leſſe to diſpenſe them, as children and women, <hi>Way cleared,</hi> par. 2. pag. 19.</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <p n="4">4. Ordination is a work of Rule, <hi>The way,</hi> p. 49.</p>
                           <p>Ordination and juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction (both acts of Rule) pertain indifferently to all the Presbysers. <hi>Ib.</hi> 49.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>4. As for election and Ordination of Officers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> theſe things they (the brethren) may doe (if need be) without Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers: <hi>The way</hi> p. 45. 101.</cell>
                        <cell>4. Ordination is not an Act of ſupream juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, but of order ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: in <hi>H.</hi> Survey part. 2.75.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <p n="5">
                              <pb n="41" facs="tcp:40476:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>5. The Key of authority or Rule is committed to the Elders of the Church, and ſo the Act of Rule, is the proper Act of their Office, <hi>The Keys</hi> p. 20.</p>
                           <p>The people diſcerning and approving the juſtice of the cenſure, give con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and obedience to the Will and Rule of Chriſt, <hi>The Keys</hi> pag. 15. 37. 41.</p>
                           <p>The brethren ſtand in an order, even an orderly ſubjection according to the order of the Goſpel, <hi>p.</hi> 11.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <p n="5">
                              <pb n="41" facs="tcp:40476:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>5. In caſe the Officers do erre and commit of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, they ſhall be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the brethren. <hi>The Way,</hi> pag. 100.</p>
                           <p>The Church exerciſeth ſeverall acts of authority over the Elders, <hi>The way</hi> p. 101.</p>
                           <p>The people have ſome ſtock of power and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in government of the Church, <hi>the Keys,</hi> pag. 36.</p>
                           <p>They rule the Church by appointing their own Officers, <hi>Ib.</hi> p. 16.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <p n="6">6. Excommunication is one of the higheſt Acts of Rule, and therefore can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be performed but by ſome Rulers, <hi>the Keys</hi> p. 16.</p>
                           <p>The Church cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate the whole presbytery, becauſe they have not received from Chriſt an office of Rule, without their Officers, <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>No act of the peoples power doth properly binde, unleſſe the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Presbytery joyn with it, <hi>Ibid.</hi> 36.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <p n="6">6. If all their Officers were ſound culpable, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in hereticall do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, or ſcandalous crime, the Church hath lawful Authority to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to cenſure of them all, <hi>The Way,</hi> p. 45.</p>
                           <p>In caſe of offence gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by an Elder or whole Elderſhip together, the Church hath authority to require ſatisfaction, and if they give it not, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to cenſure, <hi>Ibid.</hi> p. 101.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <p n="6">
                              <pb n="41" facs="tcp:40476:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>6. Excommunication is not an act of power of office, but of judgement: nor an act of higheſt rule, but of ſupream judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeated in the frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, <hi>Survey</hi> par. 3. p. 45.</p>
                           <p>As a Church of brethren cannot proceed to any publike cenſures without Elders: ſo nor the Elders without concurrence of the people, <hi>&amp;c. Pref. to the Keys,</hi> pag. 4.</p>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <pb n="42" facs="tcp:40476:23"/>7. It was a ſacrilegious breach of order, that Commiſſaries and Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors, wanting the key of Order (no Miniſters) have been inveſted with juriſdiction, yea, and more then miniſterial au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, above thoſe El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, who labour in the word and doctrine, <hi>The Keys,</hi> p, 6.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <pb n="42" facs="tcp:40476:23"/>7. There is a Key of power given to the Church (with the Elders) as to open a door of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance to the Miniſters calling, ſo to ſhut the door of entrance againſt them in ſome caſes, <hi>&amp;c. The Keys,</hi> pag. 9. yea, to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure all their Elders (without Elders) <hi>the way</hi> p. 45. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as afore.</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8. We are far from al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing that ſacrilegious uſurpation of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters office, practiſed in ſome places, that pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Chriſtians ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take upon them to preach the Goſpel pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely, <hi>The Keys,</hi> pag. 6.</cell>
                        <cell>8. This is ordinarily practiſed in old <hi>England,</hi> and allowed by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent brethren. Yea, they being but in the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of gifted brethren: no Miniſters to other Congregations, do it or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily themſelves.</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9. A particular Church of Saints, profeſſing the faith (that is, members without Officers) is the firſt ſubject of all the Church Offices, with all their ſpirituall gifts and power, <hi>The Keys,</hi> p. 31.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <p n="9">9. As the Keys of the Kingdom of heaven be divers, ſo are the ſubjects to whom they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted divers, <hi>The Keys.</hi> p. 11.</p>
                           <p>The Apoſtle were the firſt ſubject of Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal power, <hi>Ib.</hi> p. 32.</p>
                           <p>A Synod is the firſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of that power whereby error is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced and condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ib. <hi>p.</hi> 47.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <p n="9">
                              <pb n="42" facs="tcp:40476:23"/>9. The power of the Keys belongs firſtly to a Congregation of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting beleevers. <hi>Surv.</hi> part. 1. pag. 219.</p>
                           <p>The power of the Keys is in the Church of belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, as in the firſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, <hi>Ib. p.</hi> 195.</p>
                           <p>That con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                                 <desc>••••</desc>
                              </gap> is wide, to make one firſt ſubject of this power, and yet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to ſhare in this power, not by means of that; for this is to ſpeak
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40476:23"/> daggers and contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <pb n="43" facs="tcp:40476:23"/>10. Paſtor and flock are Relates: and ſo he is a Paſtor to none but his own Congregation. This is the common Tenet.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <pb n="43" facs="tcp:40476:23"/>10. The members of any Church we admit to the Lords Table (if they bring Letters Teſtimoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all) and their children to Baptiſm, <hi>The Way,</hi> p. 68. <hi>The Keys</hi> 17.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <p n="10">10. Adminiſtration of Sacraments is a Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall act, and what autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity hath a Paſtor to doe it, or they to receive it from him, to whom he is no Paſtor? M. <hi>H.</hi> Survey part. 2.64, 65.</p>
                           <p>Paſtors and Teachers might pray and preach in other Churches beſide their own, but not admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter Seals and cenſures, <hi>Bartlets modell.</hi> p. 63.</p>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>11. We receive the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lords ſupper (ſay the ſame of Baptiſm) as a Seal of communion, not only with the Lord Jeſus in our own Churches but in all <hi>Churches</hi> of the Saints, <hi>The Keys,</hi> p. 17. See <hi>Def.</hi> of 9. poſ. p. 133, 134.</cell>
                        <cell>11. Baptiſm, (and ſo the other Sacrament) ſeals up the externall communion, with a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> M. <hi>H.</hi> Survey par. 3. pag. 27. and he diſputes againſt it, is to, the Catholike Church.</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>12. It is an act of the Elders power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, to examine, whether Officers or members, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they be received of the Church, <hi>The Keys,</hi> pag. 21.</cell>
                        <cell>12. As for admiſſion, election, ordination of officers, admiſſion, and ſhutting out of members, theſe things the brethren may do without Officers, <hi>The Way</hi> 45. 101.</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <pb n="44" facs="tcp:40476:24"/>13. Ordination is then compleat, when the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have choſen him, and the Presbytery hath laid their hands on him, <hi>The Keys,</hi> p. 37.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <pb n="44" facs="tcp:40476:24"/>13. But if the Church want a Presbytery, for want of Elders, they want a warrant to repair to the Presbytery of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Church, to impoſe hands upon their elect El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, <hi>The Way,</hi> pag. 50.</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>14. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> were ordained to that office (of Apoſtleſhip) by the Impoſition of hands of ſome Officers or members of the Church: <hi>The Way,</hi> p. 45.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <p n="14">14. In <hi>Act.</hi> 13.2, 3. There is no Ordination to office at all: for the Apoſtles had their office before. M. <hi>H.</hi> Survey <hi>part.</hi> 2. p. 83.</p>
                           <p>This was not to put a new office upon them, but to confirm their ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Gentiles, <hi>Ib.</hi> p. 60.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <p n="14">
                              <pb n="44" facs="tcp:40476:24"/>14. This was done in a particular Church, <hi>The Keys,</hi> p. 29.</p>
                           <p>The Officers of one <hi>Church</hi> did what as done in an ordinary way, <hi>Surv.</hi> par. 2. 83. Then it follows (by M. <hi>C.</hi> his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine) that the Apoſtles who were Officers of all Churches, were ordained in a particular Church: or that Officers of one Church may be ordained in another Church, which he ſaid was unwarranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>The Way,</hi> p. 50.</p>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>15. What if the whole Presbytery offend? The readieſt courſe is, to bring the matter to a Synod. <hi>The Keys,</hi> p. 43.</cell>
                        <cell>15. There is a readier and nearer way: The bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren may cenſure them all, <hi>The Way,</hi> p. 45. If the Congregation be found faithfull and willing to remove an offence by due cenſure, why ſhould the offence be called up to more publike judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? <hi>&amp;c. Keys</hi> p. 42.</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <pb n="45" facs="tcp:40476:24"/>16. It belongs to the civill Magiſtrate to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh pure Religion, in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, worſhip, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: partly by civil puniſhments upon the wilful oppoſers and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbers of the ſame. <hi>The Keys</hi> p. 50.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <pb n="45" facs="tcp:40476:24"/>16. Yet the Brethren here call for or tolerate toleration of all opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and deny the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate power to puniſh any pretending conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: <hi>Bartlets Modell.</hi> 128.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <pb n="45" facs="tcp:40476:24"/>16. See <hi>M. Bartl. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell</hi> p. 25. <hi>contra.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>17. Viſible Saints, though they be hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites inwardly, are the matter of a viſible <hi>Church,</hi> M. <hi>H.</hi> Sur. par. 1. p. 14, 15.</cell>
                        <cell>17. You ſay, Saints in outward profeſſion is the matter of a Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Church: We judge that reall Saints uttering in diſcourſe the breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the holy Spirit, and experiences of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, witneſſed in a ſtricter converſation, to be the matter, <hi>D. Holmes</hi> Ep. to <hi>Way cleared,</hi> p. 4,</cell>
                        <cell>17. M. <hi>Bartlet</hi> ſpeaks ſomething this language, Can there ba ability for ſpirituall and holy ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, where the ſpirit is not yet given? Can there be communion between light and darkneſſe? can they edifie one another in the faith, that have not yet the work of faith wrought in them? <hi>Mod.</hi> p. 57. See more p. 103.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>18. The forme of the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church is the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, either explicit or implicit; and the latter is ſometimes fully ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent: M. <hi>H.</hi> Sur. <hi>par.</hi> 1. pag. 47, 48. and others.</cell>
                        <cell>18. You ſay an implicit uniting, <hi>viz.</hi> a walking and communicating with you is a ſufficient e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videncing of the Form: we ſay, their ſolemn con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of their faith, and expreſſe open covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Lord, to walk with ſuch a body of Saints, in all the waies of Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt form, D. <hi>Holm.</hi> Ib.</cell>
                        <cell>18. It is not generall profeſſion will ſerve the turn, but there muſt be a peculiar engagement, and appropriation to this or that particular body: M. <hi>H.</hi> Sur. p. 63. yet he ſaid, an implicit covenant was ſufficient.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <p n="19">
                              <pb n="46" facs="tcp:40476:25"/>19. We crave leave of the Reverend Author of the Keys, to declare, that we aſſent not to all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, or all and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry aſſertion in it: As in theſe particulars.</p>
                           <p n="1">1. About prophecying by gifted brethren.</p>
                           <p n="2">2. That the Aſſembly <hi>Act.</hi> 15. was a formal Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod.</p>
                           <p n="3">3. That the Apoſtles acted in it as ordinary El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. <hi>Praef. to the Keys,</hi> p. 6.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <pb n="46" facs="tcp:40476:25"/>19. We do in this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle certifie our aſſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the way of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in <hi>New-England:</hi> ſaving that we do not yet fully cloſe with ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, in the book, before ſome of which (ten at leaſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like there are more) we minded to note a ſtar in the Margent. This we could not but ſay and do <hi>(pace tanti Authoris)</hi> or we could not aſſent. <hi>Ep. to the Way,</hi> p. 2. f.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <pb n="46" facs="tcp:40476:25"/>19. Yet they are angry, we call for a fuller De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of themſelves, <hi>Ep.</hi> to the <hi>Way,</hi> p. 1. and <hi>Ep.</hi> to <hi>Way cleared,</hi> p. 2.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>20. It is generally aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them, that one Church hath not power to cenſure another.</cell>
                        <cell>20. A Synod hath pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to determine to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw communion from them, if they cannot heal them. <hi>The Keys,</hi> p. 25.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <p n="20">20. A ſentence of Non-communion denounced againſt whole <hi>Churches. Apol. Nar.</hi> p. 18, 19.</p>
                           <p>If a ſentence denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, it is a cenſure.</p>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <p n="21">21. We ſay, Inſtituted priviledges and ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces doe not immediatly flow from ſpiritual union and relation to Chriſt and his members, <hi>&amp;c. Def.</hi> or 9. portions. <hi>p.</hi> 76.</p>
                           <p>He muſt come at them in a right order, <hi>i. e.</hi> the party muſt be a member pf a particular Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation <hi>Surv.</hi> par. 2. p. 65.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <p n="21">21. Then it follows, that Hearing the Word preached, Singing of Pſalms and Baptiſm, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long not to any but to ſuch as are members of a particular Congregation.</p>
                           <p>And yet they ſay, ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary hearing is no ſign of a Church-member. <hi>Sur.</hi> par. 1. p. 18.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <p n="21">21. A perſon hath his firſt right to a Sacrament (and ſo to other Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) becauſe he hath an intereſt in the Covenant of the Goſpel, <hi>Survey</hi> par. 2. 65.</p>
                           <pb facs="tcp:40476:25"/>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
